of the very spirit of God and of Christ Himself.
For Ancient Faith Radio, this is Father Thomas Hopko.
And that was speaking the truth and love with Father Thomas Hopko.
Father Tom is Dean Emeritus at St. Vladimir's Theological Seminary.
This is a listener-supported production of Ancient Faith Radio.
He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him and they will...
Pray, and bless, and celebrate with Saul worship him,
They will praise, and bless,
And celebrate with Saul worship him,
And they will praise, and bless.
We will be a staff for the righteous
With which for them to stand and not to fall,
And he will be the light of the nations.
And the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
We all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
and pray.
and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 and 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons and saints.
In our time, many yearned to break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well? How do we purm-
every day life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God,
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen DeYoung,
Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
and I am Father Andrew Stephen Dayton,
and I'm Mayas Pennsylvania.
This is a pre-recorded episode,
so we're not taking any calls this time.
Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners
with help from the Theoria School of Filmmaking.
Theoria School of Filmmaking is the first Orthodox film school.
The primary instructor is Jonathan Jackson,
a faithful Orthodox Christian speaker, writer,
and five-time Emmy Award winner.
To learn more about Theoria, please visit
theoryoffilm.org. That's T.H.
eorcafilm.org.
And that's our commercial.
I think you're doing that backwards.
You think so?
Yes, like it needs to be is brought to you
with help from theory of school of filmmaking
and listeners like you.
Hey, I didn't write the script.
That to be is the correct order.
And listeners like you.
Yes.
Well, so in many of our past episodes,
we have brought up various pagan
even the communities, including God's associated with thunder and lightning,
Bale and Zeus, foremost among them, but with the occasional mention of good old
Thor as well. But we've never focused directly on them to give a rounded out
overview of who they are and how the people of God had reached out.
And how the people of God have responded to them and even continued to tell their
stories. So in this episode, we're actually going to do that.
that. We're going to move through these three basically chronologically in terms
of how biblical and subsequent Christian history treat them.
Bale, Zeus, and then Thor.
So, Father Stephen, who exactly is this Bale?
We hear so much about especially in the Old Testament.
What does that name even mean?
He's his guy.
He's just this guy, you know?
Yeah.
President of the universe.
He's out.
Sort of vice president.
Oh, okay.
Eventually.
Right.
Yeah.
So, yeah, we're going to talk about bail.
Insert bail puns here.
Don't bail out on our show before we're done.
There we go.
Strong together with bailing wire and duct tape.
Yeah.
Even if you get centipres and don't pay bail.
There we go.
Yeah, never pay bail.
So.
And of course, technically it's pronounced ball.
Right.
But if I have to pronounce it,
every time I'll episode I'm gonna feel like super pretentious right like I never
stopped you've watched I don't know if you watch Sandman on Netflix yet no like
every time they say constant time I'm like seriously people yeah I mean I know
you're British but seriously people so we're just gonna say bail okay who
We're gonna say bail, bail's plural.
People are just gonna have to deal with it.
So yeah, Bale, we have to differentiate between Bale as title and Bale as proper name.
Okay.
Right.
Because Bale or Baal means or meant and it's earliest here, just sort of Lord or master.
Once you get into Imperial Aramaic, and it's called Imperial Aramaic because it's the form
of Aramaic that was sort of the lingua from...
of the first Persian Empire.
It starts being used more,
it's still used sort of in that way,
but it's also often used for husband,
like head of the household,
a lot of familiar, it's kind of the master of the house.
And there's still, I guess, some related words
in Arabic that are used for husband kind of thing.
So, but I'm not qualified to give you the details of that,
Bye, bye.
conversations recently. So it also came to be used in various forms of late Hebrew and
Aramaic to mean master in the way that we use sort of mister. Right. People may not be aware
of that, that mister and misses come from master and mistress. Yeah. Right. I mean, and modern Greek,
it's like so called people, Kideos and Kidea, which is Lord and Lady. Yeah. And Sir comes from
and that's what I was saying.
So I was using that same way.
So for example, the famous founder of
Kabbalism, they call him the Bail Shem Toe,
but you're like, wait, Bail.
Why are they calling this Jewish guy Bail?
What's being used in that master,
right, in the same way that in Syriac Mar
or Moore gets used.
Right.
Yep.
And Sayanna means master, right?
We call her bishops best.
So it's
that kind of sets, right? So the bail could just sort of function in that kind of way. And
in the Old Testament, it's usually functioning in that kind of way when it's used in the plural.
Bales. Right. So you'll see, you know, Israel ran after the Bales.
Right. The idea there is it's just being used to refer to sort of pagan deities in general.
Yeah, right.
who have or called various things, but that's that's usually it more as a title.
But there's also evidence from very early on, right? So not only all of our
ugaritic evidence like the Bale Cycle, so we're talking about the second
Millennium BC, where this starts being used as a personal name, right? In the same
way that we're gonna see L, which is just sort of the generic early
Semitic Word for God.
in general gets used as a proper name for one particular
pagan deity. Bale starts to be used as a name for one particular
pagan deity. Right. And this this God has found having
other names in other places. The most closely
allied is the right one word, but the the most closely derivative one,
derivative one.
is the god Hadad in Syria.
Yeah, which, I mean, is that, I mean, I know the name Hadad.
We have these blacksmiths in modern Arab.
That's because that related to the world differently.
Yeah, yeah.
But, and I'm going to pronounce this the Southern way.
When you see, you're reading the Old Testament and you come upon,
Ben Haydad.
That's the son of Haddad, the son of this deity who's the king in Syria.
Right.
So we know this is the one that's most closely allied because in the very early period, the
very early Canaanite period where bail is just starting to become a proper name for this
there is Bala Hadda is the way he's
referred to and sort of very early what would be now called
Phoenician sources sources in the Levant, right? We find this
Baal Hada who ends up just being referred to as Baal by the
Phoenicians and just being referred to as Hadad by the Syrians.
Got you. There's this clear sense that this was one one person, one
deity and they're kind of using two different names for them.
Right.
right, that there was sort of an original name that incorporated both.
Right. Yeah.
Bill Hadat. Right.
Paul Hadat.
This is the Lord Hadad.
So what just started calling him the Lord and the others, I just started calling him Hadat.
Right.
My name is Robert A.
And then within that, right, we've talked about the use of the word
hypostasis to describe that we're not going to go back in.
to the discontinuities with the doctrine of the Trinity now.
But the word hypothesis is used to describe the way
in which sometimes within these pagan sources
you have gods in different places that are treated as aspects
or versions, type of stasis of the same God.
And then there are other gods who are treated as different gods.
Yeah, and there's a...
potentially infinite localizations. Right. With these pages. And so the difference would be,
for example, right, you have Artemis the way she's depicted in Athens, which is as this
huntress. And then you have Artemis the way she's depicted in Ephesus, right, with all the fruit
hanging off of her. Right. Artemis of the Ephesians, the Ephesian Artemis. Right. Right. Those
those were seen as being the same goddess.
Right, right.
But neither of them were.
scene is being the same goddess as Hera or Athena or any other. So it's not that sort of all
the pagan gods just devolve back into hypostasis of one male and one female god. Right.
It's that there's these variety of spirits and gods and then they appear in various forms
or manifest themselves in various forms in different places and different cultures at different times.
And so what you end up with is they would see
for example, Bale and Haddad, and when we read about Baal Paur, right, often you'll find a place
name attached to the Bale of this place, right? These are all seen as hypotheses of the same God.
Right, they didn't think that the Baal of Pahor and the Baal of Tyre were two different spirits.
Right, right. They said these are two manifestations or local versions of the same,
kind of spirit.
from the pagan perspective.
So that said, bail is part of a family of gods.
Yeah.
The super dysfunctional family.
Yes, a very dysfunctional family.
His and this family treat us not branch a lot.
Yeah.
So, bail's father is L, which is we were just mentioning.
That's just the word for God.
Right, so...
Submitted word for God.
So there's a guy.
God and Lord, right?
It didn't be used as proper names here essentially.
God and his son Lord.
But then, Bill also has a sister named a knot
who we've talked about a few times before.
And not only is she his sister, she's also his wife.
Yeah.
And she's also kind of crazy, as we'll see,
Lord, say, apples of.
You don't have to hedge it.
She's super duper crazy.
Yeah.
Um, Santa control.
So that sort of is immediate family tree.
As we mentioned, not a lot of branching there,
they're keeping it close together.
So the bail cycle, which is our earliest
and really only sort of comprehensive sort of story
sort of story of bail of this God, right in his.
his antics. Comes as we mentioned on the show before from the city of Hukarat, which
was destroyed right before the Bronze Age collapse. So probably was an early part of the
Bronze Age collapse. And so this is the text. This is of course on tablets, Ugaridic even
though
It's a Semitic language that's very close to Hebrew
was written in Kuneiform.
So this is on tablets in Kuneiform
and as we're gonna see in a minute,
not totally undamaged, it's not totally intact.
Yeah, and we should say that Ugarit,
I mean we've mentioned this before,
but just remind, especially for those people
who don't listen to every single episode,
Ugarit is the roughly near the modern city of Latakia
in Syria and the ruins are there.
You can go see him.
Yeah, Russia. I'm right. Yeah, the name of the place now. Right. Where?
Ougar it was dug up
The city state so
And and the bail cycle is kind of
Like one of our episodes in three parts
There's sort of three halves three sort of movements and it's the middle one that's got some damage
image where everything isn't totally.
And we've talked about all three of these parts at various times on the show before.
But just kind of go through them again, again, because this time we're focusing on bail,
and that's sort of where those different bail traditions are going to go when we get into Greek and even later European sources.
The first part is sort of about bail's insurrection.
Right.
And this is, uh, bail in his dad are not the bosses, right?
They're part of this big council of gods.
And the people currently in charge are Yam the sea, right?
It's representing sort of chaos and, uh,
Nahar, which means river.
Right.
So there's King Yam and Prince Nahar, right.
And Yam is sort of the,
The most I got who's in charge and the Nahar is...
his son, who's the one who presides over the council of the gods.
Yeah, the right hand man.
Yeah.
And Yam also has a couple of, as we've talked about before,
Lothan and Rahav, he has these sea beasts, Leviathan, Lothan,
water dragons, who he's going to end up sticking on bail during this insurrection.
that kind of that.
But so these are sort of not only the previous people in charge, but these are forces of chaos.
Excuse me.
Chaos and destruction. Right.
So, bail tries to start this insurrection. He's trying to fire up, you know, all the other gods to go and help him in his revolution.
And these messengers, the words literally the same word as A.
angel. Let's mullock. Our scent from Yamanahar and instantly all the other gods except
Bale literally put their heads between their legs, like bowed down on the ground. Like,
No, we're not doing nothing.
Yeah, we're not with that guy.
And so then bail calls them all out as wussies, right?
And gives.
some sort of this ra-ra speech, right?
No, we can do it, right?
Bail the mode of the external speaker.
Yeah.
And part of that is him saying repeatedly,
lift up your heads, oh, ye gods.
Right.
Beening quit bowing down before these, you know,
lackeys of Yavin Dehar.
We need to go and win one for the team
so they won't cause the bad news bears anymore.
Um, yeah.
So of course they ultimately have this insurrection bail totally wins
Right totally defeats
Yamuna Har
Totally makes his dad the boss instead of Yom right and he takes in a harsh place in the council of the gods
Now what's interesting here is that
despite
L always sort of being there in the background and being the most high god
I'm sorry.
He doesn't really do anything.
Yeah, he doesn't show up.
I mean, does he show up anywhere in the bail cycle?
Well, he kind of shows up later,
but he's not the one doing things and motivating things.
Yeah.
Right. And he's not even the one really being worshiped.
Hmm.
Right. It's bail, who's the focus of the worship of the temples.
Even though he's technically in this sort of second position.
Right.
So this is part of the phenomena
that we talked about way back in the long ago time in the early episodes of the show.
When we were talking about how we were talking about the Tower of Babel,
and we talked about how just anthropologically, when you study the origins of religion,
you see a primitive monotheism, what we would call primitive monotheism, the idea of
they're being one kind of
major central, most high divine figure in addition to other spirits, but who is over the top,
that that most high God figure sort of retreats into the background.
Yeah.
In favor of the worship of what are considered in the stories to be lesser sort of spirits.
And we talked about sort of why, why that seemed to happen from an anthropological perspective,
and then also obviously from the story we're told in Genesis.
ten and eleven. Right. But so that happens with L too. We can see that here with L. So this
story of Bales insurrection gets kind of rewritten a couple of times in the Old Testament.
Right. It gets what seems to very clearly be drawing on elements of this story, but flipping
them on their heads. So one of them that we've talked about relatively recently on the show
So this is an Ezekiel 28.
in the prophecy against the king of Tyre.
Yeah, right.
So the bail was by that point firmly established as the God of Tyre, right?
The central city in Phoenicia and center of Phoenician life.
and the king is seen as the son of Bale.
Sometime literally we talked about Bale.
right? Ben Hadad. He's seen a sort of the the the son and that's why in the
prophecy it is Ezekiel 28 it starts out pretty clearly talking about the King of
the city. Yeah yeah and then slides very easily into the spiritual King of the
city. Yeah I mean it starts and then it starts talking about you know this
guardian cherub who was in Eden on the mountain of God you know being thrown out.
Right, right, and so that
also describes an insurrection, it's just that Bale doesn't seem to have totally won.
Yeah, right.
In fact, quite the opposite, right?
He's hurled down into the underworld, right?
Not a great place to be.
Yeah.
So the other place that sort of takes up
of these themes that we talked about in one of our previous
Possible episodes is Psalm 24 or 23 in the Greek numbering where
that phrase, lift up your head, Zoey God's, get sort of borrowed and inverted to describe
Yahweh coming and invading the underworld.
Yeah, that's the good heads of God's.
That Gates, that Bale was cast down to.
Right, so sort of as he's kicking in the bronze gates of the underworld, he's sort of mocking
Bale's ra-ra speech.
Right.
Oh yeah, you totally won down here.
Yeah, now you're gonna lose down here, too.
Right.
And we talked about how that's ultimately fulfilled
in Christ's heroing of Hades
and that's how it gets into the Possible ritual
and other parts of it.
Yeah, and gospel of Nicodemus has Christ,
you know, has those words being said
during the herring of hell?
Yeah, yeah.
And it also gets into the,
our liturgics of the ascension,
but we'll talk about that more in a minute.
Yeah.
So that sort of...
That insurrection is round one.
So then round two is,
Bill gets into a big fight with moat with death.
And he has to fight death because he totally won that other fight.
Right, and death is down there, right?
So.
Yes.
And so part of part of what's going on in a battle between bail and moat, right?
so bail as a storm god.
the primary element of sort of his got it is has to do with fertility. Yeah, right, which may not occur to us as being a storm thing unless we're farmers.
Right. Yeah. You need to get the reins in their season. Right. Right. Right. And that was seen as sort of the masculine aspect. And then you have various goddesses associated with the earth.
Yeah, right. That's sort of the other fertility aspect.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. So the metaphorically, the rain comes down and sort of impregnates the earth
that it brings forth life, right, the idea here. And that was enacted in very literal sexual ways
in the bail cult. Right. It was sort of enacted with shrine prostitutes. Yeah. Because we have to
remember that all these religious stories that there's a religious ritual participation in them,
which often
the reenactment of some element of it.
Right, in order to get the, you know, that act is then, you know, the fertility of the
land and the rains coming in their season.
And Mo on the other side, right, is not only death.
I mean, that's literally what he's named death.
nowhere near as cute as the one in the
Just a reference Sandman over and over again.
I guess I have to watch it.
All you Neil Gaiman fans.
But he's not only sort of the god of death but also of sterility.
So the idea of death is so closely associated with famine.
And with the desert.
with a lack of, right?
And if...
If...
If you don't have the next generation of children, then your clan, your tribe dies.
So all of those ideas sort of surround mode.
And so that's why that sterility element is sort of directly opposed to bail sort of
fertility element in a way that we might not notice at first with the storm god.
Why would a storm god and death have an issue?
Right.
Zucid 80s are bros.
I mean.
Um, but we're not there yet.
Yeah, so in this fight, as I mentioned, this section is the place where we have some
breaks in the tablets.
Yeah, so we just don't know what the text was.
So we don't have all the details, right?
So we know that in this battle, Mote Swallows Bale.
It's not clear if he's dead.
Right.
When death swallows you, that makes it sound like you're dead, right?
He could just...
be inside moat and still alive, right? Or something, right? Yeah. Because what happens is a
knot, his sister wife, shows up. And in this order cuts, cuts moat in half, right? Presumably
to get bail out. Then runs the two halves through a sieve.
that takes what she gets out of the sieve and grinds it up with a grindstone, a giant grindstone,
and then takes that and like throws it out as mulch.
It's like scattering ashes when someone's been cremated.
This is why cremation is pagan.
This is why.
So, so that happens.
And this is described that in the text as bail,
totally winning the fight with Moe.
Yeah.
How do you say totally wins in the inner griddock?
He totally wins.
Flalless victory, finishing.
And then just decides to stay in the underworld anyway.
Right.
Like it's beautiful beachfront property or something.
Now I should say there are some people who hypothesize.
Right. That this section, and again, I say hypothesize because there's chunks missing.
Right. Yeah. Hypothesize that this has something to do with the transition from fall to winter to spring.
Yeah. I mean, you can see in Greek mythology, there is this association in the underworld with that with the kidnapping of Persephone and by Haydn.
So they're people who want to read it.
that way, you can certainly see how you can get there with what we have.
There's also some points of discontinuity, right?
Like that it's not that bail like emerges from the underworld and we have
spring.
It's a not comes and, you know,
that acts up mutilates and mulches.
The whole thing on his back.
That could be another, you know, another, and the next year.
for our, you know, chair,
boom, zodiac tour, zodiac tour,
it should be the mulching moat tour.
Yeah, yeah.
Get your moat mulch.
The spring.
Yeah, so I mean, could be
kind of hard to tell that for sure.
We just don't know.
It makes some sense, but we just don't know.
Yeah, yeah.
So then the third part
Uh, uh, is about uh-
They'll build a palace, right?
They'll need a palace, because he's like
totally one, all these fights, right?
And so a knot is like on a roll
and super mad at her dad slash father-in-law,
L, that he hasn't built a bail of palace already.
Because he totally deserves one, right?
And threatens to crack open his skull
And
murder her father if he doesn't get her slash in law. Yes. So Bill gets his palace, right?
Right. And this underworld palace gives us again, we've talked before about Catholic
Bull Bale, and the relations between that and the Bhaemot or Bhaemus, right?
The Bull.
And...
I believe we briefly mentioned and will only briefly and euphemistically mention here,
that the particular stuff about catholic bail in the underworld has to do with him
romantically coupling with a heifer. Right. And that was enacted richually. Yeah.
Not with two animals. In parental advisory, everybody. Yes, it's eukaryotic.
ritual life. Yeah, yeah, it's early paganism was beautiful, the Ducrystianity ruined everything.
So this sort of culminates in the enthronement of Bale, right? It is palace by L.
And so this bit here, this is how by the way the Psalm 24 to slash 23 in Greek,
material ends up with our ascension,
in our ascension liturgics.
Yeah, because it's said in a lot of the,
I think it's in the exoposterlative,
and for the ascension it says,
it's calling to the angels,
lift up the gates,
because the king of glory is entering.
Right, and the idea here is, again,
this isn't contradicting the other.
This is also throwing it in Bale's face.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, then it's not Bale's son of L
get in the round.
right that it's it's Jesus Christ the son of God who gets enthroned right and so
maybe he didn't totally win that insurrection after this is also rewritten
within the Bible in Daniel 7 right the big internal of the son of man and the
and the, uh, the man comes riding on the clouds, right? Like bales the cloud rider, right?
Eddie, he...
comes and is enthroned before the ancient of days.
Right.
Who was described there in using a lot of L language.
Yep.
And so that's a, again, a correction,
a corrective rewriting of the Bale story.
So a few other places where we see our pal Bale show up,
The old testament.
We mentioned, and we talked not that long ago on the show about Baal Paor, or Baal Paor, the
Baal of Paor, the high place where Baalum helped instigate the priestesses, shall we say.
Of that high place to seduce men of Israel into participating in these fertility rituals related to Baal
that resulted in a plague falling.
upon the people that resulted in Phineas becoming the high priest by putting an end to it.
Right. Probably the most famous place though that Bill shows up is in the story of the
the prophet Elijah, Saint Elias.
Right.
When he becomes the patron saint of sarcasm.
Yes.
And so right.
Jezebel is the queen of that point.
So Omri, as you mentioned before,
Omri from the perspective of just if you go
by the archaeological record of the ancient Near East,
Omri is the greatest king, Israel,
either the northern kingdom or the United Kingdom ever had.
Expanded the territory the most, he was the richest,
he was the most involved in trade.
he established Samaria as the capital of the...
northern kingdom. And so part of that, they called, they called Israel the House of Omrigh,
all the neighbors, right? They didn't call it 1000 David, they called it 1000 Omrigh.
And pretty much until it got wiped out by the Assyrians. So Omrigh was this very important
king. His son is Ahab, right? And so part of his wheeling and dealing and deal making
and international trade and all that was...
is marrying his son to the daughter of the King of Sidon,
tired of Sidon being the two most important cities in Phoenicia,
who had the train empire of the Mediterranean at the time.
So this was this major strategic alliance that he arranged.
So when we get to the time of Elijah,
we have Ahab and Jezebel in charge.
The bell in Jezebel is Bale.
Yeah, so it's a Theophoric, yeah.
Yeah, the thing for it.
name, right? But it's interesting if you look at the dynamic of this story, because like
A-hab is technically the king, right?
Yeah.
But is he in charge?
Yeah. It doesn't seem to be doing a lot. It seems like Jezebel's kind of the one doing
all this stuff. And it's interesting to notice how that parallels the relationship between
a knot and bail. Like in the bail cycle.
So it's not, you know, some people have this
a Jezebel woman. It's more than Jezebel's kind of a not woman.
Yeah, right? So,
Bale has this bloodthirsty sister wife, who seems to be the one doing most of the hacking
and killing and threatening and bloodthirsty stuff and all this
in the Bale cycle. And he's a little more of a passive character at points,
even though he's supposed to be, you know, become sort of the king of the gods.
And we see this kind of enacted with just
Isabelle and Ahab or Ahab just gotta like okay.
Right.
Yeah.
And she's running her out slaughtering profits at the VIAWA.
And so she sees, and this is gonna be important later,
she sees the cult of Yahweh shall we say, right?
The worship of Yahweh.
And I call it, I think it's fair in Israel to call it
the cult of Yahweh because the way Yahweh was being
worshiped in the Northern Kingdom,
Remember is based on chair bones.
sort of knee bat. Yeah. Right. The first king of the North or their king to be set up
golden calves. Yeah. It was at Bethel and Dan. Yeah. An idolatrous approach to worshiping Yahweh.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So they are worshiping Yahweh kind of. They're just doing it in a very pagan
way that he commanded them not to do it. Yeah. Right. Over and over. Like this is John.
That job one right and and so Jezebel's violently opposed to that even right right but
most especially her target is the profits because the profits of Yahweh stood outside of that
sort of official religion. Yeah, they were some clashes. They weren't the pre-stop at the
higher places. These were guys kind of out in the wilderness. Right, right. So she was a keen
on the worship of Yahweh in general, but at least she could kind of control the official stuff.
Right. Whereas the the profits were sort of wild cards, right. As her opponents. As profits tend
to me. Yeah. We've talked with.
that's the prophetic role they stay in kind of outside that system.
So she is all about promulgating this fertility cult of bail.
Right.
And so the story of the showdown with bail actually starts earlier than most people,
most people go directly to Mount Carmel.
Right.
But it's important to the story that that's not actually where it starts or it starts is
when the prophet Elijah comes walking into the thro-
road room and says the equivalent in Hebrew, because it's really rough Hebrew, of not going
to rain no more.
And it leaves.
Yeah.
No more rain.
Right.
Which is out.
Which, you know, if you're a bail worshiper, you believe that bail controls the rain.
Right.
That's the whole point of the fertility cult.
Is you're going to get the rain to grow your crops.
Right.
With bail.
So then it's...
stops raining. And Jezabel has her bail priest doing all their bail priest stuff.
Uh, do it all the rituals. Doesn't rain. Doesn't rain. Doesn't rain.
Meanwhile, St. Elias is hanging out in the Kitter and Valley being fed by probably
Ravens. Um, I don't know if I mentioned this on the show before. Here's another
are ruined your Sunday school.
OK.
It is entirely possible to read the consonants.
there. If you take out the Maseritic text vowels that he was being fed by Arabs. Oh, I've
heard of this before. That's fun. But you know, our iconography depicts Ravens, so we'll
go with that. We're going to go with that. They're Arabic agreements. Sometimes the Maseritic
Valepoids are correct.
Right.
Probably most of all of you opponents of the Bacerenic text.
Yeah, probably most of them.
So, but he's there being fed, he's got water, right?
He's okay.
So the final culmination then, right?
That's really sort of the opening battles is, hey, this whole fertility thing, he can't
really deliver on.
Yeah, right.
Which is sort of the main thing.
Yeah, you've got to soak.
But then sort of the final battle is what happens at Mount Carmel.
Thank you.
And the final battle is related to who controls the Thunderbolt.
Thunderbolt's enlightening, very, very frightening.
So this is sort of the symbol of Bale's power.
And I know I've already ruined this Sunday's cool on the show before,
but if you haven't heard that episode, I'll ruin it for you now.
And that is that the fire from Heaven that they're talking about
on Mount Carmel.
with the larger the profits of bail,
that's lightning.
Lightning.
It's not some big fiery spiral.
Like you see in the movies.
There's no word for electricity.
Yeah.
Right.
Because you know, lightning strikes,
it sets things on fire.
Yeah, right.
So obviously, it's from the heavens.
Yeah.
So this is about who controls the thunderbolt,
the symbol of his power.
So he can't deliver on the fertility thing.
thing.
right so let's go straight for his manhood right for his power and
this is why
then you get the the profits of bail trying to get him to throw a thunderbolt and
like their sacrifice on fire and you get all the great sarcasm of maybe he's going to the bathroom.
Maybe he's on vacation on a trip.
And then
you know, you get profitable,
I get doubling down and so
kick everything with water.
You know, feeling a boat of water
around the and all this and then
still right it gets cabloid,
right by the Thunderbolt comes
and then that's not the end of the
story. Then it starts raining.
Yeah. Right then it starts pouring
down rain and that's after the
people always all say Yahweh is
God right.
So he is the one who has the ability to do and controls this, not bail.
So doesn't deny that bail exists, just denies that he's worthy of being worshipped.
Right. Because his track record is a series of losses.
Right? A series of stunning losses.
I think humiliation, yeah.
Right. And then the other place where we briefly is in the story that's part of the Daniel traditions,
where exactly it is in the Book of Daniel, etc., will vary depending on the
Diversion of the Book of Daniel, even if it's in Daniel, it will depend on the Diversion
of the Book of Daniel. But the story of Bell and the Dragon, right? The Bell there, as with the name
name, Jezebel, is the neo-Bavillonian incorporation of...
of bail sort of into their pantheon.
We talked before about how pantheons don't sort of really exist.
Right. Like there's the it's not like, you know, the Greeks were all sitting around
and they all believe there are these 12 guys and ladies hanging around on Mount Olympus.
Right. Right. Like people had been up there and looked around.
Um, it's not like I'm clashed to the Titans. No.
Oh man, either version.
Right. But so what happened was individual places and clans and tribes and cities had their
individual gods. And as they form alliances and as these larger units, right, especially
empires, get established, they then incorporate, right, sort of the the the various deities
and spirits, right? And so you'll see, like for example, just in Mesopotamia.
You've got Southern Mesopotamia,
is Sumer, Northern Mesopotamia is a cod.
And for a few millennia BC,
which one of those was in power sort of goes back and forth.
And as it does,
you find these stories of their gods,
where some of their gods had become the most high god,
and then aren't anymore and get replaced by somebody else.
And that's because different cities come rise
and fall in power in different political realities.
Right?
They believe that those
political realities reflect these sort of spiritual realities. Right. That there's a direct
a direct relationship. Right. And so when Nabokulassar and his son, Nebuchadnezzar or Nebuchadrezzar
is actually more accurate, Nabokudurutzer, Nabokudinozor, as they put together what becomes called the
the knee-opaviloning and parts.
Neobabalonia, because of course, Habirabi's Babylonian Empire was more than about a thousand
years before that.
As that empire gets put together, they not only have the traditional gods of Sumeran
Akkad and Babylonia, but they expand to the West.
And so they start incorporating these canonite traditions and deeds into there.
And so, Bell, Bell gets brought in his bell.
And then there's the whole,
the, the, the of Abelonian Empire only lasts
about three generations.
So there isn't a lot of time for stuff to happen,
but there's very clearly an attempt being made
to try to assimilate Bell and Marduk together.
Yeah, and I recall in the Bell and the Dragon text,
text in that's in the Greek Daniel.
I can't remember now I stopped my head which King it was, goes to worship Bale specifically
to kind of connect to him as the local god, right?
Yeah.
And so, yeah.
And so, Bell and Marduk, like Marduk has a very similar succession myth story to Bale.
Yeah.
the issue. And so there's sort of this attempt to, are they the same kind maybe? Right? Like how
How do we, you know, fit this together?
How do we assimilate this west Semitic stuff, right, into our East Semitic stuff?
But again, it doesn't sort of last long enough for that to fully happen.
But the worship of bail and some of those areas in what's now Lebanon, Syria, what's now
rock right Mesopotamia continues until the second or third century AD. Wow.
And we have classical sources, including priests, who write about it.
And describe it at that sort of late stage.
Right.
That's even been that.
That's Roman's present in all those areas.
Yeah.
And so in that late stage, of course, it's assimilated with a lot of back and forth.
There's been back and forth assimilation with a lot of Greek stuff.
Yeah.
which uh...
will lead us into. Yeah, that's a second half. Exactly. All right, we're gonna take a short break
and we'll be back with Zeus. See ya. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing
Secret Turning, a collection of short stories by Stephen Signari.
So I'm out in the lot of little heaven, and up comes Father None from behind.
grabs me, gives me a kiss, and tells me he's happy to see me.
Where in his worn out Dungary Bibbov rolls with the beat up straw stets and pulling his
wire basket going shopping on the out.
you. How old is Na'ul, many way? Sharky asked. Older than he acts, lefty said. To be
already said, yeah, and younger than he seems. So he says to me, Theodery. The church is
much better when you're there. It's not the whole family when we don't see you. You know,
God misses His children. And Na'ulga misses her son.
available in paperback, ebook and audiobook at store.inchantface.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the second half of our episode on Thunder Gods.
Normally, we would start to take your calls,
but this is a pre-m...
quartered episode, so no calls for this particular episode.
So we just wrapped up talking about Bale and how Bale worship continued on even into a
couple of centuries into After Christ.
So and there are classical commentaries on some of that, so connecting to the ancient
Greco-Roman world.
So now we're going to start talking about Zeus.
So what's the deal with good old Zeus, father Steven?
Yes. Well, we have to disambiguate here.
Okay. Right. Zeus is not to be confused with Dr. Zeyes, who is an orangutan who bears an uncanny
resemblance to the log ever, but was never a Greek god. Wow. There might be people from the
70s listening who knows well not many yeah man
I haven't thought about those movies in a long time.
Um...
Masterpieces.
Yes.
At least the first couple.
At least the first one.
At least the first 20 minutes.
Just no.
No.
The first one, everybody's only.
Written by Rod Sterling, most people, though.
I feel like Charlton Heston is a thread
that runs through a lot of her conversations
kind of in the background, you know?
Well, yeah.
Yeah.
If I can find a way to work the Omega Man into this.
The Omega Man is the
worst remake of that story, by the way.
No, I haven't seen that one.
I am legend. The story by Richard Matheson has been adapted into film three times.
Once as the last man on earth with Vincent Price, which is actually the closest adaptation
of the actual story.
Okay.
Once as the Omega Man starring Charles Nesten, which has very little to do with the actual
story. And uh, third
as I am legend with Will Smith.
Wow.
Which the alternate ending,
if you watch it with the alternate ending,
is decently close to the original story,
with the theatrical ending is not.
I have not seen any of those films,
even the Will Smith one.
You are missing out.
Richard Matheson is an unsung writing hero.
Okay.
He wrote most of your favorite episodes of Twilight Zone.
He wrote somewhere in time.
Oh, somewhere in time with Christopher Reeves.
Christopher Reeves.
And Jane Seymour.
Yeah.
My mother got a rest or so.
She loved that movie.
So I watched it a few times when I was young.
Yeah.
Yes.
Wow.
So that's a throwback right there.
We've gone a bit far afield.
Yes.
Research the works of Richard Madison listeners.
Back to Zeus.
You got to do something in between episodes of Lord of Spirits.
there, it's you can read.
the works or watch the film works of Richard Madison.
There we go.
Um, I'm going to now to Zeus.
Um, he's loose.
Um,
so really in so many ways,
yes, on the loose,
running him on.
Um,
as we mentioned before,
uh, on the show,
um,
within this weird construct
that I think is generally bogus
of Western civilization.
Greece's offence to sort of the first Western civilization is more accurately
seen as sort of the last ancient Near Eastern civilization.
Yeah, which you've said that before and always generates a little round of questions.
Why is he saying that?
Just take it to the Greeks.
To class.
I don't know if that's bad for the Greeks.
I don't think that's bad.
No, I think so.
So yeah, you know,
The pinnacle of an earlier civilization is opposed to, you know.
initial stage of another one.
You know, the pinnacle.
But, yeah, sort of, here's sort of some of the nitty-gritty of what that means and how
that works.
Right?
So, there is, and a lot of this is, a lot of this is, is tricky because when we talk about
early Indo-European stuff, right?
We don't have a ton of...
resources. Yeah, a lot of it. I mean, a lot of it is a lot of its
filiological, which is, you know, they sort of reconstruct
proto-indio-European linguistic roots by looking at
modern languages and kind of working backwards from there with
a whole lot of, you know, if you look at linguistic
texts, folks, you'll see little asterisk sometimes in front of
of roots and stuff, and that means that we don't actually
know that that route existed, but it's our best guess based on where those languages
went. And so, you know, like you said, there's not a lot of written sources because writing
just isn't around in that period. And so a lot of it is pretty good conjecture from working
backwards, you know, from from later instantiations of things. But again, it's conjecture. We don't
really know, right? We're just kind of making a guess.
based on, okay, like we see all these civilizations that are kind of outgrossed of Indo-European
civilization that seem, for instance, to have the idea that cows are sacred. And so we
work back from there and, and oh, by the way, look, here's an archaeological dig that has
a bull's head in it. So, okay, maybe they worship some kind of bulldy at you, you know,
that's the idea. That's how it goes.
Yeah. And, and the stuff we do have tends to be very specific. Yeah. So, like we have
of Sanskrit sources like in India.
Yeah, but how close together culturally really are sort of the early
Mendoans and the people of the Indus River Valley.
Yeah, we don't super because geographically obviously a lot has happened.
In terms of migration and stuff, so a lot may have happened in terms of language
beliefs.
Yeah, I mean, you know, just think about, you know, the European language family, you know, family.
is the largest in the world. I think how different heart language and culture as English speakers
is from Persian speakers is from Latvian speakers is from you know I mean all of these are
Indo-European languages and once represented a single culture Mandarin Chinese right well Mandarin
But yes, but yes, right.
So the
So what we have is there's an Indo-European layer,
right, sort of at the bottom of Greek culture.
Right.
But everything we find essentially,
that distinguishes Greek culture
from sort of early Indo-European culture in general,
right, is all stuff that seems to have come
out of ancient Near Eastern culture.
Right? Meaning what distinguishes Greek culture from the earliest phases, right? Like
linear B, right? Like our earliest written Greek sources from the Maesanians. What distinguishes
that from other Yandu European cultures is all stuff that's been assimilated from their
ancient Near Eastern neighbors, which were far larger, more established, and more developed cultures.
at the time that Indo-Europeans migrated into the hellspawn to to
a western Asia Minor, right?
Yeah.
When they sort of arrived there, right?
So there are two sort of main places where this happens, and it happens in sort of two
different directions.
at the Bronze Age Collapse.
Right. So the 11th century BC civilization collapses, at least to their area around the Mediterranean,
but really worldwide. Yeah. And if you're, and if folks if you're interested in a really long
exploration of this, we once again recommend the Fall of Civilizations podcast, which has a whole
episode on the Bronze Age collapse hours long. And there are a ton of factors, including,
including all the way back in the-
the Bronze Age climate change, right? Climate patterns changed and it caused certain land
that used to be used to grow food to no longer be able to grow food, which caused people
to start migrating. And when people start migrating, that causes things like wars, because they
usually migrate to some place where there's already people.
Right. And so all kinds of things have, there's chain reaction, all kinds of things going
on but the whole thing sort of comes crashing down in part.
that is what's referred to by historians as the C.
People's Invasion.
So there's a group of people, they're called the C.
People's not because they're like the C.
Monkeys family in your in your old comic book.
Oh, right.
I knew someone actually bought the one who actually
bought some keys and raised them up.
Like is that real?
It got like krill.
Yeah.
Right.
Um, it's because they came from...
the Mediterranean. They came from the sea and boats. Right. And we don't know where all of the
sea peoples came from, but we know several of the groups were from Crete, which means Philistines
are also Cretans. And other Greek islands, right, and other places in that area and migrate itself.
and they attempted to invade Egypt.
that didn't go so swell. They had ended up settling along the coast of the
Levant, and that's where the Philistines come from. That's most likely where
the tribe of Dan comes from. They get assimilated. But like the tribe of Dan,
they get partially assimilated, I guess they stay kind of big. What happens
over time, we see this with the Philistines archaeologically, the very earliest
tear of like their pottery and their crafts and that kind of thing.
is looks my synate, right?
Is like confirmatory of their origin.
Yes, yeah, see that's part of how we know where they're from.
Yeah.
And so then over the centuries, as they're
living in the ancient Near East, their pottery patterns
and methods change, these things change
and shift to sort of mirror their neighbors, right?
so they kind of assimilate into.
the ancient Erystern culture, the Canaanite culture over time.
And part of how that happens is that the place where
places where we've found their oldest stuff is often in
temples to their gods. They will have these like
my senior pottery pieces and you know, chariot pins made out of bronze.
anything's made out of bronze that they can't get bronze anymore, right? But so it's just,
or like knives, household implements and stuff, black made out of bronze, right? Because it's just,
this is this ancient technology that we don't really have anymore, right? Yeah. And those
things by virtue of being old and reflecting their past and their heritage sort of come to be seen
as sacred. And the ones that sort of survive, they start putting in their temples, right? As they're
as their older things. So they're the assimilator.
goes one way where any Greek aspect of their identity
past a certain point disappears.
So when you look at the story of Goliath,
Goliath's armor is still described
as basically mycenaean bronze armor.
So he sort of has this ancient technology armor,
it's sort of like he's got a magic item in every slot.
Right?
From their perspective,
because they already couldn't make any more of that.
but so it's just...
this symbol, he sort of represents not just as a giant, but as, right, someone with his
heart, he represents this ancient antiteluvian civilization, right? So that goes the one
way. The greater influence on Greek culture goes the other way and primarily happens in
Asia Minor. Right. So modern Turkey basically. Right. And so people tend to forget.
that from a very early fate before,
this isn't something that happened with Alexander the Great
when he came and conquered everything,
that the western end of Asia Minor of what's now Turkey
were all Greek city states.
Yeah, right, right.
Troy, that's where Troy is.
Right, right.
That's where Midas was king.
That's where Cresus was king.
I mean, this is where,
this is where when sending nations of Antioch,
beginning of the
second century, possibly late first century, where he's stopping and writing his letters from
N2 occasionally as well, like these are all Greek places.
Yeah.
Yeah, but there are places that Alexander took over and sort of Hellenized.
Yeah, they were.
They were always great.
Independent.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
And if you go east in Asia Minor overland there, you run into, you know, the hit heights,
you run into right serians.
run into. So at the border there, into the trade and cultural interaction, right,
Greece sort of assimilates a lot of this from these older, these older cultures.
Yeah, right. Just like Owen Cypress, you can get raised eating kippie.
Yeah, and this isn't, this isn't something that like, oh, we've now uncovered the truth
through archaeology, right?
Like...
You look at where Plato thinks Greek culture came from.
Plato thinks Greek culture came from Egypt and from Babylon.
No, crazy. I didn't know that.
Right. Like they were kind of aware of this.
Right. Yeah.
So they saw themselves as the successors
of these ancient Near Eastern civilizations,
not as doing some new thing. Right.
So that's sort of what...
What I'm talking about, this is the nitty gritty, right?
What I would say that it's the last ancient nitty's
true civilization, right?
These are the sort of the concrete ways
that influence takes place.
And the figure of Zeus, finally now, is one place
where we see this.
Because the origin of Zeus's name
is in that Indo-European layer.
Yeah, right.
So in that Indo-European layer, one of the contents
you have is you have
a divine sky and a divine earth, right?
The sky generally depicted in masculine terms,
the earth and feminine terms.
And this part, you find this piece
of that Indo-European layer in later Greek stories
in the form of your first beings, right?
in like Hesiod are urinose.
the heavens, the sky and Gaia, the earth, masculine and feminine. This takes a form of
sort of a bowel and a cow in a lot of the proto-inter European sa. But so the names of for the divine
sky in these Indo-European languages.
Right?
The very early stage, their de-was and de-was.
Right.
right? Right? Yeah. That becomes daewis and Latin. Right? Right? The word for God in general
and Zeus, right? Zeus. Right. And Greek. I mean, the Indo-European route, again, this is one of
these asterisk routes everybody, right? Is spelled usually dy-e-w. That's the stem that means sky,
D.O. But then you get D.O. was is the D. was.
day was sort of the again it's it's it's conjecture but it's very very good conjecture
that that's the ancient proto-inducing-
That's conjecture money can buy.
Yes, right, right. That's the ancient Indo-European route stem for God is day was derived from this
word for sky. Yeah, I should mention modern Lithuanian D.E.V.S. so it's almost exactly like the
the Sanskrit and very...
very close to the Indo-European.
So, yeah, so that's the Indo-European layer, right?
And that's where the name gets sort of plucked out of, right?
But then you also have this Semitic tier, where we see parallel to like the L and Bale,
Right, where there's sort of this high God who's the father of the other but it's the
the other the storm god who's sort of the one who's really worshiped is sort of in charge of the council of the gods.
And you see that manifests in the form of chronos and zoos.
Yeah, I mean if you think about that in terms of imagery right you've got the sky.
And then storms coming out of the sky.
Right, like you can see how that idea of sort of storms and thunder and lightning is sort of derived from this larger image of the sky.
Yeah, yeah.
and cronostube, by the way, because you use the constellation.
the sudden movement starts to tell time.
Time, right?
Yeah.
To measure time.
And that, of course, is Saturn and Jupiter,
if you're more Latin focused.
Folks.
And, of course, that's very obviously the whole Roman thing
is weird because Roman paganism, you mean?
Right.
Yeah.
Hey, everything about him.
If you watched Italian films, it's sorry.
Anyway.
So all of our Italian film efficient auditors are unsubscribing from the podcast.
Yes.
All the Follini fans have just written me off.
So actually Italian zombie movies are really good.
Take it all back.
Okay.
So previously unsaid sentences in the industry.
So because you have the atrushkins who are sort of the precursors of the Romans, right?
And atrushkin religion is very much in the Indo-European mold, like a very straight Indo-European
mold.
And then once you get to something that even starts resembling the Romans, it's just assimilated
Greek.
Yeah, right.
They're just using the old probably atrushkin names.
And it's, you know, yeah, yeah, but in some cases not even that for example
Jupiter right so it's a Jupiter a geological to be kind of the same person, but the name Jupiter is actually derived from the Greek
Eopater. Yeah, which is Skyfather which means we treat Skyfather, but who within
Greek myth is the ancestor of all humans? So sort of like the Adam figure.
right and interestingly is linguist
identical to J.F.F., who, according to the genealogies following the flood of Noah in Genesis,
is the father of the Indo-Europeans. There you go. So they all point to the same ancestor, right?
It's just, again, the Greek and then the Roman culture have made that ancestor divine.
Right, right.
So Zeus then has a birthplace. He actually has several, but he's considered to have a birthplace, right? So this already
is a different conception of the divine, right, than what you find with, right? Like say Yahweh. Yeah, who has no beginning?
Who has it has no birthplace.
Right.
There's not a spright.
Like.
And so there are several of these,
Cronos and Rea, right, are Zeus's parents and
Hessians theogony.
The first cave that's identified as the birthplace of Zeus is on
Crete, that's the Dictian cave.
That goes all the way back to Mendoa and civilization.
And was a shrine, right, as Zeus's birthplace.
later on at different periods.
Mount Ida and Mount again also claim to have caves that they claim are the place
where Zeus was either born or hidden from his father. We'll get back to that in a
second. So there are sort of in in what comes to be Zeus right as he's as the
spirit is perceived in in classical Greek culture. There are actually three
elements that get assimilated to go.
So we've talked about one is that sky god figure, right?
That sort of fatherly sky god, most high god figure.
One of those is the storm god or the thunder god, right?
Who is the son of Kronos, right?
And then the third part is, and this is what's reflected in the birthplaces,
and in the caves, and in the particular locations,
is an actual human king and founder.
figure within Minoan civilization on Crete.
And there are a few places here and there that actually refer
to this, classical sources.
Right, that Zeus at some point had been human, had been a human.
This founder figure.
So all three of those get assimilated together.
And it's that human king who the memory is kind of preserved
that causes...
Zeus to be depicted in the way he's generally depicted.
Meaning as a human or a humanoid.
It's sort of human form.
He's sort of an old man's head on a ripped young guy's spot.
That's right.
That's Zeus.
That's sort of how he comes to be depicted later.
But that's as distinct from.
mentioned way back in the long ago time on the sh-
show. I know that originally the Greek gods were also
Theriamorph. They also had animal forms. Yeah, like the Egyptian gods. Right. And so we
mentioned then cow-eyed Hera, right? Which I mean, I've been corrected on that. I made
jokes about cow-eyed Hera not being an attractive image. But a bunch of random anime fans have
What told me that I just dead raw
long. But I'll leave that there. So it happened. It's a thing that happened. I was corrected
by anime fans. I'm just reporting. Okay. But so the idea was that she had some kind of
California we talked about the bull cow imagery. Right. And so it is the assimilation of that
human king into Zeus that causes him not to be depicted as a bull, like bull bail, for
example.
right. Even when Bale is in sort of a humanoid form, he often has bullhorns, right, in depictions.
So this is what causes him to be depicted as sort of the human ways, this human king, who he's
kind of visually patterned after in most of our representations. So part of the issue with
understanding this and sort of sorting out the tradition.
is that we get most of it when you read a book about Greek mythology.
Yes, like Eda Hamilton, for instance, which yeah, which is funny because the book is called mythology.
And then it's all Greek mythology and then there's like a half a chapter at the end about Norse mythology.
And nothing else.
Like bullfinch.
Yeah, bullfinches.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, I grew up on this stuff.
It's, you know, it's a good starting point, but should not be an end point.
point. Yeah. Yeah. Most of what
you're getting is Hesiod. Yeah. Hesiod's version of all this stuff. Right. A lot of is from his
theogony. Right. Right. The origin of the gods, the birth of the gods. Right. And he's the one
who puts together all these family relationships. Right. And and relates all this stuff. And so
again, because people have tended to see Greek religion as if it was sort of this united thing.
Oh, yes, we believe in these 12 gods who formed a club.
Right.
Yeah.
And the Olympians.
They take what Hesse is writing. They sort of read it as if it were the Greek Bible.
Yeah. We should mention he's seventh-eighth century BC, roughly contemporaneous with Homer.
With Homer. Right. So he's, or definitely the earliest written source we have on this
stuff, right? In any kind of systematic way. Right. You have to play over religious tablets
in linear B, but they're just like little ritual tablets. And a lot of times it's ambiguous.
exactly what's going on. Here's what I mean by that. I'll give you an example. So one of the
one of the ritual tablets from Nozos on Crete in Linear B is describing it's a ritual in which
this young woman is taken and made basically a bride of Poseidon and is given to him.
Okay.
It's kind of ambiguous exactly what they're doing to her.
right. Right. Um, very much
reads like they're sacrificing
her. Yeah. But even that is
kind of a big. I mean, are they
throwing her in the ocean?
Drowning her? Are they?
Used by a priest to the temple?
I mean, yeah, she's being
shaped to a rock. And the
crack it comes at each her is
right. Like it's not totally
clear. Or is she just like
Yeah, there's
lots of ways you can go with it.
And the language, all we have is this tablet.
Yeah, and everyone just, at the time,
just sort of just knows what that means.
Right. They've seen it. Right.
Yeah. And so we, and we don't have the stories
and those kind of things connected to it.
So that's what I mean when I say,
with Hesse, you get a kind of systematic portrayal at least.
Right.
So most of the English summaries,
like both inches are Edith Hamilton
or whatever, they're basically cribbing from Hesse,
yeah.
Right. They're taking Hesse,
putting it into more contemporary English and turning it into a sort of straightforward
English narrative, right?
Not wrong with that.
Yeah.
Right.
But, but what Hessey it is doing is not sort of writing a single story.
He's making this sort of patchwork quilt, right?
Out of all of the stories and religious forms from a whole bunch of different Greek city
states.
Yeah, which are inconsistent with each other.
Yeah.
and clans.
He's got these Indo-European bits and these Semitic assimilated bits that don't quite match up and all this, right?
And so he's trying to then construct out of that one sort of overarching story, right?
This is this is remember how history was done in the ancient world.
Yeah, we've had this conversation with you.
We've now come and identified ourselves as this people,
right? And so what is the story of all of us together as a people?
And that's got to be sewn together from all of our individual stories, right?
Now that we've come together as this unit.
And so that's what he's doing.
And so how does he then, for example,
pull together this chrono Zeus, right?
Elbele, these two figures.
And the, the, the,
Buenos, uh, Gaya, boss.
cow, sky, earth, right? How does he pull all these things together? He uses the succession
myth to kind of turn this into three generations of gods.
Yeah, but as far as we know, that wasn't a thing before he did it.
Right. These were separate traditions before he did.
Right. And so he turns this into three generations of gods where
or chronos castorates, or anos or Uranus.
And then, you know, there's the whole story with Kroes eating his children and, you know,
gets fed a rock and Zeus gets hidden in the cave.
Right?
And so that very much depicts it as in Hesse, it is very much like Kronos versus Zeus.
Yeah.
Right?
Zeus has to like overthrow his father to become King of the Gods.
Keeps repeating the succession myth.
Right.
But we...
find attestations all over the place, including centuries later, like in Plato and in
Filo of Biblos, that talk about Kronos and Zeus.
Yeah. So Kronos is kind of the chief God in Zeus as his right hand made
Besides in the council. Yeah. Exactly. That'll, that'll, you know, ancient
Near Eastern pattern. Right. That pattern of like Ellen Bale. So that
continues to exist. Right. It's not that everybody says, Oh, we're all just
gonna go with Hesse here now. Yeah.
That's still exist.
So you find like Plato in the laws, and in the critics,
he talks about how there was this golden age
when Chronos and Zeus were working together,
governing the world.
And so that's a very different picture
that went Hesse against, because Hesse
is finding ways to incorporate
these multiple traditions together.
Right?
So both of the
those traditions continue to exist separately,
despite that sort of stitching.
And so we can't take the English Greek mythology
we've read and project that into the past as like,
oh, this is what the Greeks believed.
Yeah, like the single systematic religion.
Right, like they read Hesse,
like they'd have a reading from Hesse,
when they got together to worship at the temple.
Right, like we kind of want to try to Christianize it.
Right.
And it's not remotely similar.
I mean, I...
That stuff is useful, but we just got to remember that's just a starting point just because you've read that doesn't mean you know that mythology.
Right. Right.
So, um,
Now to talk about some more sort of Zeus traditions where there are sort of parallels.
Right. In the, in the scriptures.
So I'll go ahead and say it.
Zeus is portrayed in a lot of the stories as a sheepshifting rapist.
I'll just say this right now, okay.
That's the thing that when, I mean, I have no problem taking shots at neo-paganism, the
more I study it.
That's the thing that like there are neo-pagons who want a worship Zeus, and I'm like,
you want to worship a shapeshifting rapist.
Like you can't get around that.
Like this is even in the Edith Hamilton stuff.
Okay.
And you're doing that to get away from the way Chris
She had a D has supposedly oppressed women
Like come on
So we're gonna go worship Harvey Weinstein
Yeah, right right
Yeah
Rento for the moment. I'm just like like come on have you read it?
Have you read the story?
Like even the calm down version for kids
He does not come off well
I remember hearing I remember hearing though when I know that we're off on this now
now when the the Hercules movie.
came out in Greece. Apparently there were riots because of the way they depicted, you
know, these Greek pagan traditions were so off, you know, like Zeus is a loving dad.
Oh yeah.
He's loving dad.
Oh yes.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Okay.
Zeus, the shapeshift.
Much, much more like Hercules, the legendary journeys before Kevin Sorbo, what they
That's a thing.
Yes, I just applied that it was only after that.
Where's Zina and all this?
Where's Zina wore your princess?
Yeah.
Lucy Law, as well as she was just in something.
I just acted in it.
She was in Parking Recreation.
Yeah.
Sorry, I need a moment here.
Okay.
All right.
So, it's the word you've ever.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Yeah, but so those stories, those stories are ultimately the sort of late Greek version,
assimilation of the origin of the giants, right, of the the opkallu stories from Babylon,
right? This is sort of the late form they take because what do you have? You have Zeus, this divine
and figure going to mortal women.
who he gets a handkering for and and
you're pregnant them and they give birth to these sort of demigods and heroes,
mighty men of renown, right?
Right.
This is the same kind of story.
And one of the evidences, one of the connecting tissues here,
is that the Epochaloo, for example, are all Theriamorph.
Yeah, meaning beast form.
Starting with the very first one, he hit Lou.
is like half fish, right?
And you notice in these stories,
when Zeus does this for no apparent reason,
with no apparent logic in the story,
he transforms into some kind of animal.
Right.
Yeah, it's weird.
Like, you know, there's the swan,
so I mean, this is like a were swan,
a were bull, and a were snake.
Yeah.
But yeah, but like I mean it's it's it's kind of counterintuitive right like if you're a guy
I mean yes your head looks like an old dude, but like you've got the ripped young body
And you're gonna go try and seduce a woman you turn into a swan
Right, this is somewhat counterintuitive
Yeah, right?
Meaning yeah, I'm sorry. Yeah, it's it's maintaining the sort of pharium or
status
of the divine beings in those older stories and retaining the fact that this is kind of a
cross species thing happening, right? That this is a mixture, an unclean mixture of things, right?
So it's a way that shapeshifting element is a way of maintaining those elements from those
those older story, the older versions of the story.
Yeah.
It's so weird.
Um, um, don't worship Zeus people.
Yes.
Where should be Zeus is bad?
Okay.
So, so more giant stuff.
Yeah.
So, uh, you have not just through Hesse, but you have this idea, and this is,
This seems to be common.
I mean, you always have a, the succession myth sort of always has this. You find this also sometimes in other Indo-European
later developments too, where you have sort of two tiers of divine beings.
But when you put that together with the succession myth, you end up with something like the Titans, right?
You've got the Titans, you've got the gods, right? And the Titans are sort of this earlier tear, right?
Yeah.
Um, of gods, it's sort of when I ride, right?
Of course they get impressed.
The first reason in Tardarus, the one place in the New Testament where the term Tardarus shows up,
it's where St. Peter is referring to the place where the watchers, the angels who send in Genesis 6 are imprisoned.
That's where he drops Tardarus. So St. Peter makes that direct connection.
So you have this earlier too that's in prison, but they are we're seen as
the children of Gaia, right, the earth.
And so she is angry about it, right?
There's a lot of angry violent women
and they should pay against them.
Yeah, right?
It's not just a knot, right?
Like Gaia sort of loses it.
I mean, Harris always go around trying to kill off
Zeus's illegitimate progeny and their moms.
Yeah.
and the tape.
Or turn them into spiders.
I love it.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um, and
Gaya becomes sort of the mother of
monsters, right? Right. In order to
avenge the Titans, right? Take
vengeance for the Titans. So she
brings forth the giants, which
leads to the gigantic Oma
key. And then finally she brings
forth Typhon, who is sort of this
giant beast that rises out of the
sea and that is made up of all
of these horrible animal parts.
Right. Uh, kind of like the, uh,
not the demon
organ on stranger things like the actual one, the real one from
Dungeons and Dragons. That's the real one. That's the real one.
And Typhon is this beast from the sea that's sort of
wreaking destruction on behalf of these fallen angelic beings
shows up both in Daniel and Revelation in the form of the beasts
sort of theetherium or beast that come up out of the sea.
Right, are sort of referencing this.
And in the case of Daniel, it's talking about the Seljukids, the Greeks,
in the case of Revelation, it's talking about Rome.
And they're again sort of subverting the story where
in the mind of the Romans, for example,
Rome's civilization, the greatness of Rome,
reflects the divine, right, reflects their gods,
their gods who
that's the most repeated
typhon who defeated the
giants, right? That's sort
of there. And so when
St. John flips that around
and says, no, you guys are
the chaos monster, right?
Rome is the beast from the
state. Rome is the chaos
monster. Rome is Leviathan.
Right. That's whose power
thing. Right with...
with the Greeks and the other empires,
other world empires, who he depicts.
So there's another place where our zoo stories hook up.
Another one that we've mentioned before on the show,
when we were talking about the Epochalo,
and we were talking about Genesis 6,
it's sort of the revelation of this divine knowledge
to humans is the Prometheus story.
Now notice though in the Prometheus story,
Who's the good guy? Who's the bad guy?
gets flipped. Yeah, right.
For me, this is like an upcaloo,
given that secret knowledge to human beings,
fire, whatever.
You know, and humans love him for that.
Thank you, Prometheus, but it makes God's
a bit. Right.
So you have this divine being who reveals
the forbidden knowledge to humanity.
He here is the good guy.
Right. And the mean old God comes and, right,
it presents him and and punishes him for it.
Yeah, internally.
It's almost, I mean, it's almost a Christian narrative.
Right.
You know, except just, you know, the good guys and back guys are flipped, but yeah.
Yeah.
Making a good example of Pro-Devil propaganda.
Pro-Devil propaganda.
Exactly.
Oh, this was good.
This was good when he did this.
And so, relatedly, right, another connection here is in, at the beginning of the book of
in the letters to the seven churches is a letter to
to Pergamum or Pergamum, depending on where they're using the Greek or the Latin name.
Where St. John refers to them living in the shadow of the throne of Satan.
Yeah, right.
And so if you're ever in Berlin, you could go to the museum and see the throne of Satan.
Right, because they got it.
Yeah.
And that is the great altar to Zeus that was there that
picked in its carvings, the defeat of the giants by Zeus,
winning the Gigantomaki.
So again, this is how the Romans saw themselves.
Their civilization had conquered the Earth,
the monsters that come out of the Earth,
and established order.
civilization, right? And that was the place we're in that city. That was a famous altar.
And anytime the emperor or any of his generals were passing through, they stopped there, especially
when they were on the way to Eastern campaigns to offer sacrifices there. It's belching
for smoke all the time, right? And St. John can very easily call it the throne of Satan,
even though it's an altar to Zeus, right? We know the connection between altar footstool
of the throne, right? We've talked about that before.
Right. And the reason he can do that is that by the time St. John is writing at the end of the
first century, sorry, Prederus, St. Irenaeus tells us when it was written. We know that by that time,
the idea that Baal equals Zeus, right? And therefore, for a Jewish person who had read the Hebrew
Bible and knew that bail equals the
devil, right? The transitive property gives us a zoo,
equals the devil. Yeah, right. Right. And so these are seen to all
be the same figure. Right. And the reason that's firmly established
by the time we get to St. John at the end of the first
centuries that way back in the fourth century, BC, Alexander,
the great had already kind of established it. Yeah. So when
Alexander the Great.
in his push eastward, right? God in DeSiria, he came to one of the ancient shrines of Bale,
right? And he sort of publicly reconsecrated it and offered sacrifices there to Zeus Boenergies,
which is roughly Zeus the Thunderer, right? And in doing that, he was declaring that the spirit
worshiped there, who had been worshiped there as Bale, was actually a hypostasis of
of Zeus. Yeah, so they're not
really two different gods.
They're the same right.
This is just the local instantiation.
Right. This is the local Asia
localization of who Alexander
worshiped as Zeus and considered
to be his dad in snake form.
Yeah. So, um, so related to that,
you know, we got a question about
that term, bow and urges.
Um, so David Thompson who is just
beginning as a seminary and at
St. T. Con seminary. So
Good luck to you, David.
He sent in this question.
We hope you survived the experience.
Yeah.
That's right.
He sent in this question.
He said, is the naming of James and John in Mark chapter three
to be bowenerges, sons of thunder, also a reference
to the twin sons of Zeus, castor and Pollocks?
Was there likely a temple nearby that Jesus was using
for a pun?
Do we have any hagiography that show James and John
to be replacements in divine counsel wise for those gods?
So that's his question.
The answer is yes.
Yes, right?
So yes, some of it and not to all of it, right?
It's not.
Yeah.
That was a broad.
Yes.
So this is said, if you look where it was said in Galilee,
this is in one of those areas, right?
Where Zuzbo and Ergie's had essentially become
the name for b-
right, like where that sort of assimilation started by Alexander the Great had taken root, right?
But so, um, Christ is kind of doing a pun. It's not directly referring to
Caster and Pollocks, I don't think. There are people, there are people who will try to go that far.
I mean, you got to write journal articles, right?
Distant.
I think that's, I think I'll say it too far because I think what Christ is doing is these actions.
chastising them with that title. Because when you look at what instigates that, right, it's
that they want to call down fire from heaven, i.e. lightning, as we already said, right? They
want to throw thunderbolts and blow up these cities for not having accepted Jesus, right?
that is message. Right? So we want to wipe them out. Right?
And I think we mentioned on the show before the episode in Acts in Listera, where
St. Paul and Bartomis get worshiped as Zeus and Hermes.
Yeah, right. Right.
That part of what's going on in the background there is there's a story that's recorded in
Ovid from that region, where they believed that at some point in ancient times it's sort of
again a late version
of Sodom and Gomorrah.
The Zeus and Hermes had come to that region and looked for a place to spend the night
and everybody told them to go pound sand.
Except for this one elderly couple who welcomed them in.
And so the next day they were awarded the elderly couple by turning them into a tree.
Grats.
But everybody else, they destroyed.
Yeah, right.
Let's not have that happen again.
Quick, here's the car.
Right. Right. So what Christ is kind of doing here is pointing out that they're kind of
imitating the wrong God. Yeah. If they're attitude. Right. Right. Right. Because
wherever to be the son of something means to manifest those characteristics. Yeah. Right.
You don't want to be the son of Boa Nerji's. Yeah. Right. That's not who you want to be.
right. Don't act as
So yeah, he's trying to move them away from the vengeance
and more towards the mercy and the compassion.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
All right, and with that,
we are gonna take up quick break
and we'll be back with Thor.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-238.
That's 855 AF radio.
The Ancient Faith Content Creator Conference is back this September to connect writers,
podcasters, artists, designers, and influencers with uniquely orthodox networking and professional development opportunities, including keynote addresses by
Father Andrew Stephen Daymeck, Cassie Ne and Melissa Laro.
and sessions with ancient faith staff and contributors on the public forum, design, publishing,
podcasting, children's books, digital marketing, storytelling and research.
Invited speakers include Derek Cummins, Brian Jarbo, Nicholas Kossar, Nicholas Kutar,
Phoebe Farrag-Mikhail, Nicole Rokis, and Christina Tartara.
Find out more about their sessions and register at store.
AncientFace.com slash
events. We're back now with the Lord of spirits, the father Andrew Stephen
Damick and father Steven DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855 237 2346.
That's 855 AF radio. All right welcome back. We're talking about the war now. So
So this actually follows on really well.
Because everything we really think we know about Thor comes from the Christian era, right?
From Stanley and Jack Kirby.
Yeah, from Stanley and Jack Kirby, who are I think they're both Jewish, aren't they?
Yes.
Jack Kirby, definitely.
Yeah, I think yes.
Everything after Kirby went to DC is apocryphal.
Oh, that's true.
So like Mike Deodato's leather
Thor outfit apocryphal.
It's like his tertolian moment. He became a mountainist and just everything after that.
Well, no, his DC work was good, but it's just he left Thor.
Yeah. So Thor then pushed it off and do strange places.
He got new secret identities like it.
Right.
It never made sense again.
Yeah. I mean, so, you know, that's that everybody.
I need you to, whatever you're thinking about Thor, that has to do with Chris Hemsworth or the Marvel Cinematic Universe,
or even the old comics, you just need to set all that aside.
very little of it has actually to do with Thore and Norse mythology. I say the
nay. Right exactly like Thor talks that way but if you actually read the way he
talks in the mythological sources he's kind of not particularly a Shakespearean
orator you know or sounds like so the guy the King James Bible or a foe Shakespearean
orator. Yeah right right and it's almost like you know it's like we're talking
by those Roman gods earlier, right?
Which are basically the Greek god...
with different names mostly, although occasionally the same name, I think isn't Athena on both sides.
Yeah. Well, because Athens is Athens. Yeah, right exactly. So you can't. Yeah.
You know, that the Marvel comics, as guardians, the S- here as they are called in the actual sources,
are very different characters, but they're kind of using the North's names.
Right?
And you know, one of my little rants,
I'll just throw this out here right now.
In the Marvel Cinematic Universe, you see Sif,
the goddess, who, I don't think she's actually
Thor's wife in the movies, right?
She's Thor's wife in the sources,
and she's a brunette in the films,
but it's like, we'll get into this, I'll get into this.
I won't go into this.
Thor's a blonde.
So in?
Yeah, well, right, right.
That's also an accurate, well, anyway.
I don't want to get too ahead of myself while I hear...
color. Um, but well, so sif so there was a there was a whole there was a period of time where sif
was joined to Jane Foster, the way Thor was joined to Donald Blake. So that was she got her
her her. So sif has been a romantic figure. Okay. Terms of Thor. All right. In the comics. Yes.
In the comics. Yeah. Yeah. Um, right. So anyways, just said most of that stuff aside, uh, it's not
you
really super relevant. But I mean, it's important to say that not just because, you know,
why would anyone take those stuff seriously? Anyway, when it comes to mythological studies,
I'll dare you. How do you? I like them as stories. They're fun.
Marvel version is the only one that's still alive. Yeah, okay. That's true, actually, in a big way.
Yes. Although, well, there is this esachro thing, which I'm not even going to go into right now,
but I will get to that.
But because you can sometimes see, for instance, on the internet,
like I just ran across a meme the other day,
which shows this picture of this Thor figure.
He's got a hammer over his shoulder.
And it says, you know, your God was crucified on a cross,
but mine has a hammer, right?
And so like, that's the image that people have.
And I think that's largely derived from seeing Thor
as a kind of superhero in the comics.
especially, but especially the movies is where a lot of people are counting a character named Thor.
So we should set that stuff aside. So as I said, almost everything that we know,
quote unquote, about Thor and the Norse gods is from Christians. Right? Now, before I get into that,
someone is probably in the back of their head is saying, well, what about Tacitus? What about
Tacitus with Germany? Yeah, you know, which is like first century, okay? So Tacitus, who is this
Roman.
historian he wrote this text called Germania. And most of it is actually not about the gods.
Most of it's about, it's things that he has heard about the way that Germans live. Now,
you know, Germans for him is not like the modern nation's state of Germany. It's those barbarians
living up somewhere away north of Italy and such, right? That's what Germania is for him. It's
that area. Now he never went there.
You never went there. He is compiling sources. He's apparently did talk to some people that went there.
So we should not consider him to be a reliable source. And the other thing is that he interprets a lot of it in terms of Roman language and culture, which I mean that's totally understandable, right?
He's that's his perspective, but also the purpose of his text is actually to kind of
antique Roman culture that was current to him at the time by kind of depicting this sort
of noble savage that was the Germans, the Germanic tribes.
You know, and I cowl how sort of pure and primitive they were and look at how corrupt and
decadent we are, which I mean he was certainly right about that part.
You know, and it was the idea was like, you know, they're like we used to be back during
the Roman Republic days, you know, that's kind of what he was trying to do with that text.
So, anyway, if you can read your
centuries for them to become that way.
Right.
Yeah.
You know, and the thing is that
between that and the sources that
are normally pointed to is the
Norse mythological sources.
There are 13 centuries.
That is a long, long time.
So we shouldn't look at that text as
being an accurate depiction.
of Norse religion. He, for instance, says that they worship Hercules, which, who might be
a Thor figure, at that point in Germanic history, Germanic pagan history, we really do not know.
But he says, you know, it's said that that Hercules visited them and they have this alter to Hercules.
Actually, he even mentions that they worship Eulisys. So it's interesting that he
he shows them
worshipping as gods, people that Romans and Greeks would have regarded as sort of superhuman
heroes, you know, human heroes, but superhuman heroes, you know, maybe semi-divine, right?
So I just wanted to get that whole Tassas and Germania stuff out of the way, and the other
thing I'll say about that is a lot of, like, frankly, the Nazis and people who are into
So that kind of thing, I have read TAS, this is Germany as
sort of proof of the the glory and the ancient purity of of that people and I've used it to very
nefarious means. Tacitus would have no idea that that was going to happen with this text.
I'm not saying people shouldn't read it. Just be aware if you do decide you want to read it,
that that's being used for that too. But anyway, I would not take it as a good source about
Germanic religion or mythology or anything like that. There's some interesting stuff in there for sure.
But it's not really where you're gonna go if you want to understand.
the sources of North mythology. Okay, all that said. So all the actual written sources that we have
about North mythology are from Christians. And most of them are Icelandic. We're talking,
you know, 13th, 14th century, a lot of it, mostly 13th century. Why is that the case? Why is it so
So, certainly weren't there people worshiping Odin and Thor and so on?
before all that. Yes. So for instance we've got St. Boniface and the 8th century
goes up there, chops down a sacred oak. There's references to him in his life
confronting Germanic pagans, but we have nothing from that period from pagans. Right?
And if you read St. Slives, they're not going to tell you a lot of details about
Pagan mythology and religion.
It's just, there's just not there because it's not from that point of view.
So that information is not there, right?
Why don't we have that kind of information?
Well, the reason is that unlike the classical Greco-Roman world,
Northwestern Europe, which is where this stuff is happening,
doesn't really write very much at all.
We have a few like inscriptions on things,
some bits scratched into rocks.
We have
with people's names, you know, stuff like this.
But the combined amount of text that we know
that was written by Germanic slash Norse pagans
is really, it probably could not even, you know,
make up a paragraph or two total, right?
Like that's the amount of actual writing we have from them.
So that's why we don't have it.
Writing, reading and writing in real literacy
and manuscript production all this kind of stuff.
It comes into Northwestern Europe with Christianity.
So we simply do not have sources.
We do have some archaeological stuff, which again, you know, you find something that's buried
down in a bog or whatever.
It's not going to tell you much of a story.
It's not going to really tell you much about religious practices, right?
Like, you know, imagine a church that's been buried for centuries, right?
And you dig it up.
Are you going to know how to celebrate the divine liturgy by doing that?
No, you're not.
Right, even if you know that the divine liturgy was celebrated there, you're not just it's not going to be there. You're not going to have that information.
So what do they dig up in archaeology? Well, they dig up sacrifices sometimes. So they find armor and weapons and stuff like that shoved down into bogs a lot of times.
And occasionally they find sacrificial animals, but also sacrificial people.
So often where their throats cut, so there is animal sacrifice going on.
And the reason that we know that some of these places were sacrificial sites to gods like Thor is because of place names.
So that's one of the ways that ancient ways of thinking about a place are preserved over time is place names.
So you get, you know, we've talked about theophoric people names, right? People who have names that are connected to the names of gods or include the name of the god.
You have theophoric place names as well and often a see
if we're a place name means that that place was worshiped,
that that deity was worshiped in that place,
that there was a sacrificial cult going on there, right?
So like we, you know, you mentioned rather Athens, right?
That's the place where Athena is worshiped.
And so the city became named after her.
So you've got a number of places.
What's that?
Thorville.
Yeah, right, right.
That's exactly what you're talking about.
So there's a number of places in Scandinavia
that have names that include four.
in the name or some variant thereof. Interestingly, although like, although that's more,
Thurve is more like a, it's actually a feminine name, but it probably is a Theophoric name.
The Day of the Week. Yeah, yeah, Thor's Day, right? Yeah, Thor's Day. Sorry. See, I'm just, I'm just, you know,
going off, so I'm not even hearing you. Interestingly, even though Odin is depicted as like a king of
the sources that we have. We don't find too many
theophoric place names with Odin's name on him.
So all indication that we do have is that
Thor is the God who has worshipped the most,
from what we can tell.
It's possible that the idea of
Odin being above all, above everybody else,
Everybody else in worship the most is a leader in vengeance.
So, you know.
Well, as we talked about being above everybody else,
does it necessarily mean worship the most?
You're right.
I mean, the opposite.
Yeah, in the background.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's interesting.
Yeah, I mean, we're not talking about Odin today so much,
but Odin shows up in a lot of sagas,
which again are later Christian stories.
He shows up as a guy who likes to kind of meddle and,
you know, poke things in the background
and wander around.
Yeah.
Yeah, he's a wanderer. He's he's associated with
Cross. Like Odysseus. Yeah, right, right. Exactly. Right.
He's associated with prophecy and with aristocracy,
with with cross-dressing magic.
We talked about that in the prophecy. Yeah, exactly. Yes.
This is total thing. So yeah. So anyways,
where do we actually get what we have? So, so I say all that to say that
But there is no sort of pure pagan source.
We don't have Norse pagans talking about their religion.
And I even talking about their stories.
We simply don't have that.
Everything that we do have is written down by Christians.
And I mentioned earlier about Asatru and heathenry, this kind of modern Norse neopaganism.
It may well be that someone is successfully worshiping Thor.
They're offering sacrifices to him and they're eating it.
That is worshiping Thor.
But if they say I'm doing what my
ancient Danish ancestors did false. We do not know what your ancient angels ancestors did.
We just don't know. So they might be, they're creating a new religion of Thor, but the old religion
of Thor is gone. You know, the last thing that the Norse pagans did, they became Christians. They
did that. So, you know, Norse neopagans is a modern religion. It's a new religion. It's not an
engine religion.
I just wanted to mention that.
Get that all in all that.
I'm kind of glad they're not killing people
and shoving them in peep-box.
Right.
Like the little bit that we do know about
there are just practices.
Maybe there's no.
General improvement.
Right.
Exactly.
Forming metal bands.
Yeah.
Right.
Not my favorite kind of music,
not even my second or third or tenth favorite kind of music,
but definitely better than cutting people's
throats and shoving them down in box.
And then you got to make an album cover
where you're wearing a lot of makeup
and you look like you're lost in the-
woods, the more sweeten. Right, isn't that what Vikings were, right? Yes.
Lost in the woods somewhere in Sweden. Yeah. The fun thing is most Vikings we know about
were Christians. So, right. But were they good Christians? That's another question, you know?
It depends on what that means. Yeah. They're at least formally Christians. Vikings that like to
raid, you know, the coastlines of Great Britain, probably not Great Christians. And a lot of them were
actual Rob Monasteries yeah a lot of those guys
were actual pagans. They actually were real pagans as the local Christians
attested. So then they used the word heavano to refer to them, right? So that's
heathen in Old English. So, okay, so what do we have in terms of actual sources?
The biggest source that you're gonna want to look at, if you want to look at the
most authentic, again not authentic, but the most authentic representation of
this mythology is written by a guy named Snorris Tore.
So Snorris Dorsen is a 13th century Icelandic politician actually. He's the the law speaker at one point,
which is sort of like the head of the parliament. But also, and he gets involved in a lot of politics
actually and he gets assassinated as a result of that. But so he's a Christian. He's he does not seem
to know Latin, but he knows people who knew Latin and he has some idea about classical
pagan sources, right? Because he references them and then many what he writes. The major book
you're going to want to look at, if you're going to look at the sources of Norse mythology, is
something called the prose edda, edda. Sometimes it's just simply called edda. In Icelandic, they call
it snora edda, snorees edda. And the, this book was written around the early 13th century.
and it is not
It is not the equivalent of Edith Hamilton's mythology.
He's not trying to put together a book of Norse myths.
So that's disappointing to begin with.
Not has he had not even opened?
No, he's not doing that.
That's not his agenda.
He's trying to put together a textbook.
And it's not a mythology textbook.
It's a poetry textbook.
So, snorey.
was it seems a pretty good poet actually. And so he was really dedicated to a type of poetry
called Scaldic poetry, SK-SK-AL-DIC Scaldic poetry, Scald is an old word for a Norse poet.
And apparently it was falling out of fashion in his day. And so he wanted to revive it.
Like, you know, other kinds of poetry, he'd become hip and cool at the courts of the Scandinavians,
So he was trying to bring it back.
And he realized that a lot of people couldn't even
write Scaldic poetry because they just
didn't have the capability.
And so he puts together a textbook.
And the purpose of this textbook is
to give you the vocabulary that you need
to write Scaldic poetry, right?
Well, why does he tell mythological stories
and service to that purpose?
It's because Scaldic poetry includes lots
lots of allusions.
to Norse myths in order for it to actually just work. Right? So I'll give you an example. We talked about
SIF, right? What is the color of SIF's hair? It is golden. It is always golden. It is nothing but golden.
And that's because the phrase SIF's hair is used in scaldic poetry as a reference to gold.
So like, you know, I might say in his hands, flowed with SIF's hair. It doesn't mean that he got up next
the goddess and was grabbing her hair. It means that he had a lot of gold. He was a wealthy guy.
right? So, Scolic poetry is full of that kind of stuff. It's everywhere.
It's like reading 18th and 19th century poetry. If you don't know the classics,
you won't know what's going on. You won't get it. So, for him, these stories are the classics,
and but they're kind of starting to get forgotten. Now, it should be said that at this point,
we are about 200 years after Christianization in Scandinavia and in Iceland.
And none of these people who wrote this.
stuff down had ever met a Norse pagan because there simply weren't any left. They were gone.
You know, Christianization had taken full hold, right? So he, the two main parts of Snorries
etta are the Gilfeginning, which is the beginning, and then the Scald Scupper Mall. So the Gilfeginning
is a kind of Q&A between Odin and disguise as a kind as a king named Gilfee.
who goes up to these three, I don't know, spiritual sages of a sort and asks them a series of questions about the gods, about the beginning of the world, the end of the world, stuff like this.
So it's a kind of cosmology is what kind of comes out of it. And from this you get a lot of the stories about, you know, Ragnarok and all this kind of stuff.
And then the Scolts Scupper Mall includes,
there is a prose portion at the beginning.
And then a lot of it is quoting some lines of poetry
and then just explaining what specific references mean.
So it's almost like a kind of thick glossary, right?
You can see how this book would not be great
for just deriving a bunch of Norse mythology from,
because it's not made for that.
At the beginning of it, he's got an introduction
in which he depicts the origin of the Norse gods.
and he says that they're heroes from the Battle of Troy.
that come north and they're like great sorcerers or something and they become
worshiped as gods by the locals. So this is called eohameraization which is
interpreting divine beings as actually being humans who then later get
worshiped right as their sort of legend grows and you can see how that's
that connects like with what Tacitus does where he says that that you know in
Germany, they worship Ulysses, right?
And in turquoise.
And so he says that the, you know, that's the origin of things.
But a lot of the things that we know of as Norse myths are all found
and especially the, the gulf beginning, which is at the beginning.
So like you get Ragnarok, you get Odin with his brothers, Villion Vey,
killing Emir, the giant, primal giant, and whose blood then fills the world and causes the flood.
Right. That stuff is all there.
there. Okay.
And then he's got another significant work called the Himes-Kringla, which is the history of the kings of Norway.
And at the beginning of it is called something called the Ingligas-Saga, which is the, you know,
and in that he very explicitly makes the Asyr ancestors of the kings of Norway and Sweden.
So he's claiming that they have this sort of almost divine origin, but again he says that the Asyr the Norse gods are humans.
Right.
That's my wife recently had this experience on ancestry.com.
No, it's crowdsourced.
Right.
So she was going back in some Swedish ancestors
and discovered she was related to Emir.
Yeah, right.
The frost shot.
The time for the frost to.
So there you have it.
Yeah, exactly.
So yeah, yeah.
So the other thing I'll say about that is that Snory is unique amongst
or Norse authors in describing the flood.
Like I mentioned, the thing with email.
Apparently your wife is descended from?
Yes.
My ancestry to the cup.
Yeah, and if anybody out there has a descent from Angosex and Kings,
you are also considered a descendant of Odin.
So congratulations here, Odin's and Odin's and I don't know how you pluralize that,
Something good though, really.
Right, Odin, it's not great.
Another major source is the poetic edda.
It is a 13th century collection from a manuscript called the Codex Regius,
which don't get confused, there's more than one codex with that name.
I mean, it's the Codex of the King because it was presented to one of the Kings as a gift.
It's a collection of songs and poems.
It's generally thought that some of these might actually be authentically pagan.
So maybe closer to the pagan sources, we don't know, though,
because once again, this collection was put together entirely by Christians.
When it was found, it was called the elder, etta, because it was assumed that it was a lot older, but actually it's later than Snorries etta.
But Snorries etta still gets called the younger etta and some sources.
But it's just this collection of poems and interpolated within it you actually have.
say interpolated. We don't know, we don't know. You have comments, Christian comments every
so often, like for instance there's one that says, this story comes from a time when ignorant
people used to believe in reincarnation. So like that's something that's there. So you get
Christian commentary. It is much harder to read unless you know the stories that are behind the poems.
So I recommend that you read, if you can read the stuff, you read Snorries work first,
which tends to present the stories a little bit more coherently as narratives.
because they're highly elusive. A lot of these might be hymns or like folk songs that often assume
you know the story, right? I mean we can kind of that kind of stuff in text we talk about all the time.
We don't know the rest because whoever heard this beginning at the beginning heard new the story but
you know no one bothered to write the whole thing down. Thanks ancient people or if they did we lost it.
We just laughed it so.
I will also give an honorable mention to a text called the Jesta de Norum. It's the history of the Danes by a guy named Saxo Gramaticus.
Gramaticus is a nickname that meant he was basically really good with Latin. His Latin is really, really good. It was written in Latin, comes from the late 12th, early 13th century.
It's basically history of the Danes from ancient prehistory up to the 12th century. It includes a very little amount of references to Norse mythology.
again.
sex with grammaticals as a Christian. So he's not trying to represent Norse mythology,
but he does engage in this eohamorization basically says that the Norse gods are people,
they're humans that got worshiped later, and he says that they're the ancestors of the Danish kings.
Another thing you'll see that's really interesting and this kind of connects back to some of the
themes that we talked about earlier, especially when we talked about Zeus is there is this connection
back by a number of these Christian authors with classical mythology.
So right, let me talk about Tassus early.
He was not a Christian, but Tassus says there were some
Hercules up there.
If you went to a local Germanic tribesman and said,
so you were supposed to Hercules,
I'm sure you would have no idea what you were talking about.
But these authors connect some of the stories,
and certainly the gods back to classical gods.
So...
Like Snorian one point says that Thor equals Jupiter.
Right. He doesn't use the word the name Jupiter, but he kind of makes this reference.
But another he's not consistent with himself by the way everybody.
And another point he says that Thor is Hector.
And the way he gives it is it's Hector. He's like this tour part. That's Thor.
It's really bad at homology, but but there you are. He lived long before the invention of
modern philology. So
So, Saxo Grammaticus says that Thor is equal to Job, although he says some say that he's
equal to Job.
He's not actually taking this position himself.
So there's this attempt to connect them back.
And again, like I said, Snory at the beginning says that the Assyr, the Norse gods are heroes
from Troy who come north and settle and rule and are worship later.
So there's this.
So that's kind of I feel like we should have said that today's work.
was you hammerize it. You
hammerization. The time we say it.
That the kid should scream real
out. I feel like we should have
said that back at the beginning.
Wow. Is this our first P.
We's playhouse for Trump?
Possibly. I think so.
Yeah, you hammerization. Yeah.
And I guess isn't it right that
the church fathers do this in some
places?
There are a few places. Yeah.
Yeah, where they talk about
particularly when they talk about
like the visual representations.
Oh yeah sure.
like who the statues are of.
Yeah.
And we should say that this doesn't necessarily
contradict with the idea that the gods are actual spirits.
Right?
Because think about all the relationships
we've talked about in terms of humans and these gods.
You've got guidance and demons.
Right.
You've got god kings, you've got humans
who can become demonized and function as demons,
who jump in and engage in idolatry
just as much as fallen angels do.
So it's pretty slippery.
None of these authors are saying that evil spirits and evil gods do not exist.
That's none of them are saying that. Right. So it's just a question of who they decide
actually is some kind of fallen angel and who's a human or maybe used to be a human.
So all right, so Thor himself, he's the Thunder God from Norse mythology,
and you can see Thunder gods that resemble him in various places,
especially northern European literature.
You've got Perkunis amongst the bolts, a very similar figure.
Actually, the hammer thing is related in there.
You've got Perun amongst the Slavs, again, a very, very similar figure.
It seems like almost every mythology has a thunder god in there somewhere.
Perun is also very similar to Thor in Marvel Comics, people they forget.
that he was a member of the Soviet version of the
Avengers. That's right. Oh man. Along with the Crimson Avenger. Yeah, right. And yeah. Wow.
Man, that's digging out pulled old memories for me. I was I was much more into X-Men.
Which isn't that a euhamerization, right? The X-Men. Humans with superpowers.
I think if I remember correctly, in Avengers versus the X-Men, the Soviet group appeared.
That's maybe why I know about him because I wasn't a super yeah big Avengers guy. Yeah, yeah
Yeah, if the Avengers had to bring in Magneto after he destroyed that submarine. You always got to bring in Magneto
Yeah, you regret it, but
Yeah, cuz he's kind of a sympathetic villain nonetheless
He killed 150 people in that submarine
And gone trial before the World Court
And he also plays Gandalf who Tolkien describes as an Odinic wanderer
So there you go, it brings us all back.
So Thor, okay, so the name Thor, we talked about names a lot.
In a lot of early sources, he's Thunar, often spelled THU-N-A-R-R,
in Old English as Thunar.
This is just literally the word for thunder.
His name is thunder. That's what his name is. It is thunder, right?
Right. As we've seen a lot of you be confused with
the barbarian. No, definitely not. Who was also created by Jack Kirby. Right? I know.
I know. And then the thunder cats. Yeah. So yeah, although there's nothing really thunderous about
them. No, not really. I don't know what what the deal is there. So it's as better than just calling it
cats. Yeah. Right. They are chasing around as you you know the laser pointer. Yeah.
the line of laser pointer of the sky.
Sky, I'll come running.
Yeah, yeah.
So Thunar, and again, the word just means thunder.
That's all it means.
And when Norse people heard these stories,
they would not have heard them as,
oh, this is someone who has this name,
and it's a different, like it would just be thunder.
So for them, the difference between the thunder
and what Thunar is doing,
not a lot of space between those, right?
This is the thunder, right?
So.
Thor is also referred, is also generally depicted as the son of Odin, who's actually Oven and Norse sources Oven.
And here's where it starts to get weird. His mother is a goddess named Yurus, and she's actually a giantess.
So, 4 is half giant, half astute.
So, you'll notice if you read nor sources that giants are...
a pretty complicated set of beings, whatever they are.
They're probably not really tall.
Some are depicted as hugely tall.
I mean, Emirates, right?
This giant that you construct the universe out of
by killing him.
He must be pretty big.
But a lot of them are basically the same size as the ass here
because they intermarry, right?
So that's going on.
And then some of them give birth to monsters and stuff.
So what exactly are giants?
It's not clear, but the giants of folklore
that we often think about the really tall giants,
like everyone always asks us,
you know, aren't giants really tall?
That depiction of giants always being tall
is a leader kind of folklore thing.
It does exist in legendary and mythological material,
but it's not what it's about.
That's not what makes them giants.
Right, and size is a way of conveying power and strength.
Exactly, yeah.
Yeah, right.
In portrayals, right?
That's a way of...
communicating power and strength.
Yeah, yeah.
I mentioned earlier, you know, Thor is married to Sif,
the golden haired.
Again, Sif's hair is never called any color except golden.
Snory says that Sif is sible.
So he's again classisizing, you know, bring his back.
As I mentioned, what was that?
Closed enough.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
Right.
As I mentioned, he seems to be the most worship God
Norway and Iceland based on archaeological stuff.
He's depicted as red bearded.
That's a major thing.
He's a great big red beard.
Hair is red.
Another thing and see, this is something I don't think.
Maybe you tell me if this ever shows up in the comics.
In the mythological sources, Norse has a wetstone sticking
out of his skull that he entered into a battle with a giant
Grung near and so Grung near prefer.
his preferred weapon was this wetstone, and he would throw it at people.
And when it hit the door in the skull, a fragment of it lodged in there.
And Thor tried to do something about it.
But the the serious that he was working with got distracted.
And so it is stuck in his head kind of permanently.
Does that ever show up in the comics?
Not not in the comics.
Yeah, and not in the movies.
I mean, hello, he should have a big rocks sticking out of his head again, very disappointing.
He's depicted as the sort of the
the big brute of the gods. He's super strong. He's not noble. He's not smart. None of these things you
see in the modern Marvel depictions, although lately they've kind of depicted him as a little bit dumber,
but he's pretty dumb in the Norse sources, which may be a function of Christians writing about them.
Right?
You're not going to depict pagan gods as being these very wise.
No pull at-
purple beings. They're going to be depicted as, you know, not that purple, right? But he
defends the gods against the giants against the monsters. He's generally a big foe of the
giants. Kills them almost anytime he sees them. He's the patron deity of farmers and sailors.
Why would that be? Because he does the weather thing, and weather is super important to both
farmers and sailors.
He's the Thunder god, he's the Storm god, right?
So yeah, also very known for the hammer, Mjolnir.
Also got a pair of iron gloves,
a big belt of divine power, makes him strong.
Here's one of my favorite things about him.
He owns a pair of goats.
Two goats, one named Tan Yoster
and another named Tan Grisnir.
And these names mean tooth nashar and tooth grinder.
Here's what's great about them.
So if he gets hungry, which Thor often-
his hungry. He can kill them and eat them. And if he lays the bones on their skins, when
he wakes up in the morning, they're back. So he's got these magical, reviving goats,
reincarnated goats. Whatever they have been in the movies now. Really? Oh, I haven't seen
the latest film. Okay, spoiler alert everybody. Yeah, they're the trailers. So, yeah, yeah,
They come back when he kills them.
to get eaten. Oh yeah. What a goats for if not to eat to pull your chair. Oh there's that too I guess,
but yeah. So, so there's lots of stories about Thor in the sources. A lot of him about him going on
various adventures and killing giants. A lot of them. And a lot of those are pretty funny actually.
I'm going to mention one of those and then I'm going to tell you kind of the two big stories
This is the
that are where Thor is involved.
So here's the kind of fun one.
So his hammer, Mjolnir,
which is really important,
obviously for the defense of the Assir.
Get stolen by a giant named Thrimir.
And Thrimir steals the hammer and says,
I'll give it back if you guys send me Freya
so that I can marry her.
She's one of the Assir, she's one of the goddesses, right?
And...
And so there's a whole conversation amongst them about what they're going to do about this
and Freya of course hates the idea of having to go and be married to this giant.
And so what they do is they decide I'm still laughing about this. They decide to dress up for
in Freya's clothing because that's going to be convincing, right? So he goes and drag
And they're like, here is your brat.
And when they sit down at the wedding,
feast. Three mirror notices that Thor is really putting it away. You know, he has this
divine level of appetite. And it's like, well, what's the deal? And Thor, as Freya says,
or it might have been Loki, actually, I think that I think about it, who's nearby.
Anyways, they can, they communicate like, well, you know, she's been fasting all this
time to prepare for the wedding.
for you. And he's like, really, and sort of kind of pulls back the veil a little bit and sees
these fiery eyes and it's like, what's the deal with that? You know, like, oh, well, you know,
she's been suffering so much from all the fasting and so she's not feeling well.
And so then finally, they say, well, you know, where's the, where's the dowry?
Where's the bride price? And so they bring out Mule Near and they hand the hammer to Thor
As soon as the story gets his hammer back.
He pulls off the women's clothing and proceeds to kill just about a very, very present
and walks away.
And you know, everybody's depicted as pretty ridiculous in this story, including Thor,
especially Thor, which some scholars will say this is an indication that this was written
really late and definitely under maybe entirely composed by Christians.
Like again, we don't know which of these mythological stories were written by Christians, whole cloth
We're a debt.
by Christians were maybe possibly represented fairly authentically from the pagan period by Christians,
we simply do not know. We don't know. This is what we've got. Right? We can't say this is the original.
We have no idea. Right? So, okay. So, here's the two kind of big stories about Thor that I think
are especially important for us. But are the ones you should, I think if you can remember any,
This
So one is the fishing expedition and then the other is Thor at Ragnarok.
So if you look at the poetic edda and this is referenced in Snorries' edda too.
But if you look at the poetic edda there is a poem called He Misch Vida, which means Himmier's poem.
So Hemer is a giant. He's kind of a frost giant, a wintry giant.
And he's been staying with him in kind of eating a
amount of house and home as Thor is wanted to do.
But the giant can't kill him because there's this whole hospitality thing. You don't kill people who are staying under your roof
Even if you hate them and are you are their mortal enemy like it?
This is not a thing you do that even the gods and giants are sort of bound by this rule
and so
They decide to go fishing because he mirrors losing all of his food
While they're out there a Thor decides to rip off the head of one of he meters
uh, uh, oxygen and he lowers his line down in the water.
with the ox head as bait and what should try to get hold of it, but the midguard serpent
itself, Yoramun Gauntra, the serpent that encircles the world, right? And if he starts moving
his coils and there's earthquakes and it might be the end of the world kind of thing.
So he drags the midguard serpent up out of the water. And as he's got hold of it, he
takes his hammer and he bashes it in the head. And in some versions of the story, that's
the end of the midguard strip.
But the kind of the main versions, it doesn't actually kill him.
But when that happens, he may are realizing what's going on,
and that actually Thoris threatening to cause the end of the world.
He goes, he cuts the line that Thor has the midguard serpent on,
and then the serpent falls back into the water,
and then Thoris so mad that he goes and punches him in the head,
and in some sources, he may fall overboard and drowns.
So let's...
fishing expedition. This would probably remind us of references in the scripture to Leviathan,
this is in Job, for instance, right? Leviathan being drawn up out of the water by a hook and
tamed, right? But this is the Norse version. So it's not about taming the serpents about smashing
them in the head. That's how it goes. So the other big thing that we should point out,
the other big story is Thor at Ragnarok. And it's interesting, if you look at the actual sources
about this. There's not a lot.
In almost every one of the sources you look at,
Ragnarok is not this drawn out battle
that you read a lot about.
Like it takes up maybe a paragraph or two
or you know a few stances of poetry,
it's the end of the world.
You know the gods get killed
and some versions a handful of them do come back
like Baldur comes back,
although he had already been dead by this point.
And Odin gets killed because he gets eaten by the Fenderus Wolf,
and then reswalth aka fin
who is a an offspring of Loki, and the Midgard Serpent, by the way, is also an offspring of Loki,
and Hell, the goddess of the underworld, because in Norse mythology, the devil is a woman.
She's an offspring of Loki as well, not to mention, of course, the Odin's horse.
Slip near his locus, offspring, because Loki can be both male and female,
and also does the shapeshifting thing.
And weirdly, has children when he goes in shapeshifts.
shapeships. So this is sort of like Zeus, right? You know, you
got the shapeships.
flandering, flash-raping going on. So Thor faces off against the Midgard Serpent at Ragnarok,
does successfully kill him, but a lot of the dragons Poison gets on Thor and the sources
that says he staggers back nine pieces. The Serpent dies, but Sodus Thor who was poisoned, right?
I feel the saving throw.
He failed his savings over his poison.
That's right.
So that's the end of Thor in the actual North
sources.
As you can see, he's not depicted as being
this uber-powerful being that humans must contend with,
right, to the way that's, for instance,
Bale and Zeus are within the actual pagan context
that we know a lot more about.
What we have is a depiction written by Christians.
Again, centuries after Christianization took hold.
So, you might ask the question like, well, why would Christians even tell these stories?
I mean, they're about pagan gods and all this kind of stuff.
Well, number one, they don't actually preserve pagan religion in terms of practices.
So, you're not going to learn how to worship these gods from these stories.
It's just not there.
Christians have every reason not to preserve that kind of information.
Right?
Why would they tell these stories?
So, well, number one, remember from the point of view of Snory
and these other Christian writers,
we don't know who put together the poetic adab, by the way.
We don't know.
And it's possible that Snory had a kind of committee
that helped him do what he did.
We don't know.
But from their point of view,
these gods are actual human beings.
They're legendary humans.
So these are legendary stories for them.
And remember, Snory is trying to put together a Scaldic poetry textbook.
That's his purpose.
But even if, you know, he didn't regard telling these stories as being inherently
sinful from a Christian point of view, occasion, he does say things like,
now you shouldn't believe that all this actually happened.
Like he'll say that, right?
For him, they're just stories largely speaking, mostly, you know, he does
believe the ass here existed that they were humans.
These Christians have no...
a problem elaborating on these stories,
they have no problem altering these stories
as far as we know.
Again, we don't have, quote unquote,
originals to compare them against.
Why do they do that?
Because that is how legends and their transmission work.
That's just how they work.
They're just retelling stories.
And we should point out, of course,
that even though we do actually have a lot of pagan texts
from classical paganism
and some of these other things.
and Semitic paganism, the reason that those texts are preserved over the years largely speaking is because Christians felt that it was useful to copy them and use them.
Right, so even though we don't have much in the way of Christian quote unquote, tampering with the stories, altering elaborating on them, they're copying them.
Right, they're interpreting them, they're using them.
Right, so this is a thing.
This is-
absolutely things. So this is part of how Christian Union has kind of digested the mythology, the
leftover stories from paganism. The difference being that with the classical world,
you have, and even the second-template Jewish world, you have texts that exist as texts.
Right. Right. And so the relationship is a little different than when you don't have a text.
right and it's how are you going to record this story
that has been passed down orally to this point.
Right.
So as we've said before, once you put something in text,
it becomes a sort of literary monument.
And so this is why you don't get like Christians going
into Hessean and Homer and these other texts,
changing details and like lampooning them,
the way you sort of see with some of these North stories
is because the text already existed.
And so that monumentalized it.
it.
So they would write a commentary on the Iliad that would be correcting things and inverting
things and doing things from a Christian perspective, but they kept the text of the Iliad intact.
Yeah.
Because remember for Norsemen writing and manuscripts is basically Christian technology.
Like, that's just the reality.
I mean, you might wish some of my wish that it was different, but that is the historical
reality.
We just don't.
It's not the Christians destroyed a bunch of stuff.
that came there before them, it simply wasn't there.
We know the religion was being practiced.
Like we find a whole bunch of probably
mule neater pendants, for instance,
archeologically from the centuries
right around Christianization earlier.
We don't know what they were used for.
Interestingly, from what I understand,
about 10% of the pendants that they found
that were that are hemorrhaged were found in graves.
And I don't know why this is a
case and I don't think anybody knows the majority of them were women's graves.
What's going on with that? We just don't know. You know, you can't extract a
religion from finding a hammer pendant that someone wore a hundred neck, right?
And then also like some people look at that as being like an alternative or an
answer to the Christian cross whatever. Like they'll adopt that now and be like,
well, we don't know what these were used for back in the day. They might be
some kind of amulet they might be who know.
but we don't know, and we just don't know.
Just don't know.
There's just big blank spots, right?
So the last thing I wanted to kind of mention about Christian kind of digestion of this stuff
is the elements of these depictions, especially of Thor, right, were retained.
And in some cases, baptized.
Now by that I don't mean that people started worshiping Thor.
or anything like that. I just mean that the imagery connected with Thor got recycled.
So a good example of this is St. Olaf. So St. Olaf is the patron saint of Norway.
Now he lives right around the time that Christianization is taking hold. So he would have been familiar,
directly familiar with Norse paganism.
He's one of the latest...
scenes right before the period of the great schism between East and West and the church.
Early 11th century of Eric Hall.
And he's regarded as a saint within a generation of Eric Hall.
And earliest depictions of him show him clean shaven, right, which is probably how he looked
we don't know but that's how he was depicted.
clean shaven. As time goes by, eventually, especially after the early 13th century, so we're
talking a couple hundred years, he starts getting depicted with a big red beard. That is a
Thor image. Along with that, he's also depicted in some legendary texts as a killer of giants.
That is a Thor image, and is generally a kind of protector against evil forces and demonic
Monsters and stuff. Again, that's Thor stuff, but you remember we
talked about Christ and so forth, he's described as the writer of the clouds. It's not saying,
you know, Christ is like Bale, it's saying that actually that belongs to Christ, that title belongs
to Christ. So you get this beginning of saints using this imagery from pagan mythology, but now
Now it's been so many centuries since that was even believed in and practiced that they have
problem appropriating the imagery for this new patron of the place, St. Olaf.
So before we go to break, I just want to give a quick recommendation.
If someone's actually interested in really learning Norse mythology from the sources we
have, and not simply from the kind of collections and stuff of fairy tales and legends, which
can be interesting, right?
But are kind of largely aimed at children and so forth.
is a book.
called the Norse myths, a guide to the gods and heroes by Caroline Larrington.
And her work is very good. It's a kind of summary, and it's all entirely based on all these traditional sources.
So, all right, well, this is going to be different from other episodes, and that we actually have three breaks. There's four halves to this episode.
So we're going to go ahead and take precedent.
Unpresentative. Our third and final break, and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and fathers.
Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord
of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
For all of us, male or female, parent or not, that's what it's often like, isn't it?
at the end of our own tubs.
that the miracle happens. It is in our greatest weakness that God strength is known. It's
when we decrease that he can increase. It's in losing our life that we find it.
To put it another way, it's in the spot where Saint Morena falls down, exhausted that
her spring rises up. It's when the people of God curse Moses in the wilderness and
and wish themselves back in Egypt that they hear the crack of the staff.
of water through the rock.
It's when God himself is spat upon and mocked and bleeding and dead that the glorious
resurrection is ushered in.
From seven holy women, conversations with saints and friends, now available as an audiobook
at Audible, Amazon and iTunes.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Steven DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-
2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back to the
unprecedented 4th half of this episode of
The Word of Spirits.
This is the 100-page
Super Spectacular of the Word of
Spirit episodes.
Exactly.
This is the last episode of our
second year of production.
So the next episode is going to be our
anniversary episode.
Unlike other 100-page
Super Spectaculars, we have
No
reprint material. That's right. That's it. You can
I can build by a version that costs another 50 cents
sometime in the future. This is it.
All right. So we've talked about storm gods. What about the
fact that, you know, the true God Yahweh is associated with
the weather? Is he just some storm god who made it big? Got a
Bible, big religion based on it.
No. No. All right. And the reason we have to say that is that probably the current consensus among old testament scholars is that Yahweh is a storm god. Yeah.
Or started out as a storm god is probably pantheon somewhere. Right. And then sort of over time.
I'm Vieto.
Yeah.
sort of became the God of the Bible.
Which, I know we've said this before,
that why would any human being take a pagan God
that you can kind of make deals with and manipulate
and get things to do things for you
because he needs something from you,
wants something from you, can take a bribe.
Why would anyone ever make that kind of
God into one that needs nothing from you and commands you.
Like, why would you do that?
Something that gets since it all.
That's just how it works.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, I mean, that's not a God that any human being would ever invent.
You know, yeah, yeah.
And that scholarly consensus is based on nothing.
Nothing like there's no actual basis for it.
There is no actual basis for it.
There is no real basis for it.
it. Okay. So if you try to push, right, or when they're trying to, I'm not going to
say argue for it because again, that implies that they have a consistent chain of arguments
that produces this result, which they do not. They simply do not, right. And I mean, I've
criticize this to people with people.
the H.D.'s an Old Testament and had them literally their responses, well, that's the scholarly
consensus.
Right.
Like, that's the argument.
Like, no, everyone believes this.
Oh, well, it must be true, then.
Right.
Everybody's saying that.
Like, you know, hey, the rest of Old Testament scholarships going to jump off a cliff.
Here I go.
Right.
Bye
So, when they're presenting it, right?
When they're saying, okay, here's our presentation
of this position that Yahweh was a storm god.
Here's how they try to present.
So, they've got a basic problem, right?
Which is that if you're going to say, well,
Yahweh was a storm god who was part of one of these
Canaanite pantheons, right?
So first of all, they're shooting the
pantheon idea way back into history. Yeah. Yard where it really belongs. But anyway,
if they're going to say this kind of thing, right, then you would expect that we would have
some kind of written or other source that includes the always part of a pantheon.
And there is no such thing. Yeah. There literally is no such thing. He is not listed in any of
there.
the gritting material. Right. The name doesn't appear. Name does it appear in any, right?
Any of these lists of deities doesn't appear in like place names outside of Israel.
What's Israel is a thing, right? None of that. If it, in fact, the way I've mentioned before, I think on the show,
I'll test it out, Professor, my undergrad,
lost in younger, the way he tracked.
what happened to the 10 Northern tribes when the Assyrians deported them is by looking for people with
Theophoric names with Yahweh in them. Yeah right right because there's no one who's not in Israelite who had one
Mm-hmm in the ancient world
Right, so not only is there no evidence that like
Yahweh was part of a pantheon at some point in the past
right? There's no evidence that he ever
was assimilated into a pantheon when Israel and Judah were conquered. Right? Like there's
just no evidence for any of this. So, what do you go with? Well, there's only one place
that we've mentioned it on the show before. There's only one place outside of literature
directly connected to Israel where you see the name Yahweh. And that's a couple of Egyptian
inscriptions from the 12th and 13th century.
We've mentioned this before. Refresh everybody.
Where it refers to Yahoo, which is a shortened form of the name Yahweh, of the Shasu Bedouins.
And Shasu Bedouins were a way in which the Egyptians referred to like the Edomites, the Midianites, the Ishmaelites, right?
the sort of southern desert Abrahamic,
no thematic.
groups. Okay, so that they refer to Yahweh as being the God of these people. Right. And we've
talked about this before on the show in connection to what are sometimes called the Yahweh from the
South traditions and the Old Testament that talk about Mount Sarah, which was the center of
Ida Mite territory as being the mountain of God, mountain of Yahweh, of Yahweh having sort of come
from there north to aid the Israelites in conquering Israel.
the Canaanites. That language is there. Of course, Moses goes and encounters Jethro, the Midianite
priest. It becomes his father-in-law. So those groups were still worshiping Yahweh. They had received
it from Abraham, from their ancestors while Israel was in Egypt. So they pointed that. You say,
how does that help them? Well, it doesn't really, but here's what they try to do. They try to use
is that you
my dialect of old Canaanite and suggest an alternative etymology for the name Yahweh
and say oh we'll see Yahweh in that dialect this could be the third masculine singer singular verb
He blows.
It's like...
Yes, he blows.
And...
and based on that. And so that means see he's a storm god. That's not a lot to go on. I mean,
we looked at these various storm gods and there's way more going on there. You know,
that's so you were being kind of mean to old snorey about his etymologies, right? But,
I mean, he's doing just as well as modern Old Testament scholars, really. Would you think about it?
maybe even better in a couple of hectares right right
right? That's it. That's what they've got. Wow. That's the
quote unquote evidence for this. And that's all the evidence
for this. Right. So what is it actually built on if it's not
built on evidence? Well, it's built on a bunch of presuppositions
right? Right. Right. Undefended presuppositions. And
basically those amount to an evolutionary view of
relationship religion.
Yeah, and that's this idea.
that you've got ancient polytheism, people's primitive.
Yeah, primitive polytheism, worshipping a whole group of gods
and over time they kind of reduce the number, right?
Right, well, first, first you get heathenism.
Yeah.
First, one of them is kind of the boss of the other ones.
Right, right.
And then theoretically, you just keep
exalting that one higher and higher
and demoting the other ones.
We're telling a very...
eventually you become a quote unquote monotheist and you just forget about all the other ones
and which again the boss one is the only one left.
Again, posits human beings that go from a God they can manipulate who needs something
from them to God.
They cannot manipulate needs nothing from them and to whom they owe total obedience.
Right.
It's just not a human thing to do.
We don't come up with that.
So the pre-supposition is that this is just how things work.
Right.
So this evolution is how things work.
Pre-steposition one, pre-steposition two, polytheism is more primitive than quote unquote monotheism.
Which is also a pre-steposition.
Because you could equally argue as anthropologists, et cetera, have,
that there's actually a primitive monotheism that got complexified into polytheism.
That it went the exact opposite way.
also with
evolutionary presuppositions, right? They agree with the first presupposition. They disagree with the second one, right?
So you don't even have to disagree with all of these. I disagree with all of these, but
even scholars are not united and agreed to all of these.
So polytheism is more primitive than monotheism, and monotheism is a thing,
modern monotheism, the belief that only one God exists, only one divine being exists,
This is a video.
point that was held by anyone in the ancient world, even in late antiquity.
All of these three things are presuppositions that are either based on nothing or in the case of
the third one demonstrably false. Right. Right. So that's what this is based on.
This isn't so anyone who comes to you and says this, like I said, even people who are actually
people with PhDs, they're def-
this is, it is the scholarly consensus.
Yeah, like, but the emperor has no close people.
Yes, there is no argument for it.
Right.
And so what's the alternative?
Well, we can see the alternative by actually reading all the sources we have.
Right?
Yeah, which is, which point to, for example, the fact that Yahweh, as we've said before,
on the show is actually a hit feel.
third masculine singular of the verb to be.
Yes, so the one who causes things to be.
Who causes to be?
Right. He who causes things to be.
The creator, right?
Basically the creator.
Yeah, you don't have to look very far
in the Hebrew Bible
to see that the preeminent attribute
that is described the Yahweh the God of Israel is creator.
Right.
Not fertility.
Okay.
So that it is the creator, right? He who causes things to be. And over and over again, we
get this phrase starting in the Torah, starting with the Exodus of the creation of Israel,
where before when God describes one of His mighty actions, this goes all the way through
to Ezekiel in the exile, right, in the value of the dry bones, then they will know that
I am Yahweh.
And this gets obscured in the English because they don't put, we've talked before on the
show about why we go ahead and say Yahweh when we're translating these passages because
if you say, then they will know that I am the Lord.
That means something different.
Then they will know that I am the Lord is, then they will know that I am the one in charge,
then they will know I am the one who rules.
Then they will know that I am Yahweh means, then they will know that I am the one who
causes things to be.
that we're not. I'm the creator. I'm the creator. I'm the Israel was not a nation, was not a people. Now they are a people. And so they know that he's Yahweh or with the dry bones.
When I call your debt out of their graves, then you will know that I am Yahweh. I am the one who causes things to be.
Right? Who causes things to live. Not then they will know that I am he who blows.
right. Yeah, then they will know that I'm the storm God who
brings for.
That doesn't even make sense.
Right.
Yeah.
They're related to the creation
they're not having to do with the storm and fertility God.
And not only that, right.
One might notice that L, right, even though it's just L
is just the word for God, right?
Like Allah in Arabic, right?
Yeah.
So it's the word for God or the word God in English, right?
It's the word for God.
It's very rarely used to refer to Yahweh in the Hebrew Bible.
And if it is used, it's used with a suffix like LL-ion, right? God most high, or LFDI, or you know, fill in the blank, right?
There's some suffix. What you get instead is Elohim in the plural.
Why?
Well, because the Hebrew Bible is everywhere disambiguating that they're not talking about
You
is dead. Right. Because bail is a
not using a going concern right
nearby. They're not using L is
a proper the proper name. Right.
They're not talking about the
same. Right. And so I know we've
said this before on the show, but
it was a long time ago. You'll
often hear that L. O. He was this
plural of majesty. Right. It's
compared to like Queen Victoria.
You know, we are not amused.
It's great.
And so that's what Elohim is, right?
That's why it's in the plural.
That's not exactly right.
Right?
Because people who know their Hebrew will immediately throw back at you that there is no
plural of majesty in Hebrew, and they're right.
There isn't.
But what there is is in Hebrew, the plural used is an intensifier.
Right?
So that means Elohim is like God of God's, or the great God, or the capital G God, or
I'm going to...
with the definite article.
Right.
Yeah, I mean, English does this too.
We mentioned, you know, capital letters, definite article.
But like, for instance, there is a repetition that exists in spoken English.
You know, you almost never see this in written English.
I had no recall ever seen it because it would be hard to convey,
because it requires inflection.
So, you know, we will sometimes repeat a word if we want to indicate
that what we're talking about is
The most authentic, the most real, right? So for instance, let's say
someone has a
biological father and a stepfather, right?
So I might say I'm talking about your dad dad
And by that by repeating the word and by inflecting it that way, they mean that you're biological father
You know that's what they yeah or or it's not just like a YouTube video. It's like a movie movie
a movie movie. Yeah, exactly. Like a movie movie like in theaters. Right. Right. Exactly. Right. Yeah.
So it's that kind of idea. Yeah. And he met this is the same kind of word. The hemo the beast of beast. Right.
Just super beast. Yeah. The one that you wanted. Yeah. And so that's what's going on with the name. Right. And with Elohim that's used to refer.
Right, to the same God.
right? And that's that's really clear in the Hebrew. Right? Like, this isn't something that like,
this isn't like, oh, well, only a Christian would say, like, you don't have to be a Christian,
you don't have to be Jewish, you don't have to believe that any of this is real and true. This is,
that's like, you know, linguistic data from Hebrew, right? So slang. You can agree or disagree
with what the Hebrew Bible is saying, but that's what it's saying, right?
We should all be able to agree on it.
that right? We may disagree on whether it's true but we can at least agree on what it is saying.
New Testament scholars do this all the time. I don't know why old Testament scholars can't do this but
New Testament scholars, we agree all the time. Hey, this is what St. Paul is saying and people who
think he's making it all up and people who believe every word of it agree. This is what he is saying.
It's not that hard.
So...
Then what do we do with there are all these times, right, some of which we've already mentioned tonight,
where language about bail in particular, so storm god language from the ancient
year east about bail or had to add or whomever, get sort of attached to Yahweh.
So for example, one of Bale's titles, as we already mentioned, is the cloud rider, right? You see
see the son of man on the
the clouds in Daniel 7. We already talked about Daniel 7. How this is like an inversion
or flipping of the the enthronement of Bale story. But Psalm 104 or 103 in the Greek versus
3 and 4, this is the Vespers Psalm in the Orthodox Church. Right, it talks about God walking
upon the wings of the wind. Right. That's Bale language. Isaiah 19 verse 1, this happens
again right or bails defeat of Leviathan
of Yom of Nahar, right? That language is applied to Yahweh, the God of Israel, like Insolven
74 or 73 Greek, 89, 88 Greek, 93, 92 Greek. Job 26, 12 through 13. I feel like Jack
Van Nipy just rattling these. I say I have 51, 9 and 10. I say a 40, 26, 45, verse 12.
These are all passages you can look them up or you can just believe me.
The talk-
about Yahweh defeating Leviathan or the sea or the rivers, right?
Dominating them, commanding them, right, ruling over them.
There are things that the bail cycle attributes to bail, right?
So you say, okay, well, that could be more evidence for that other theory, right?
Just, you know, Yahweh and Pailer, like the same guy, right?
or like, you know, Thor is the old hairline guy who fights against him.
Gart Serpent. Yeah, yeah, these are these are all just the same guy. So here's the problem with that,
right? Because the other view assumes that Yahweh was at some point in a pantheon with Bale.
Right. And with these other gods, right? And so it doesn't make a whole heck of a lot of sense
for the same attributes, the same deeds, the same titles to be...
ascribed to multiple gods within the same quote unquote pantheon because that's not how pantheons
work. Pantheons are built. Yeah, the most simulation. The most you get right is where you get a kind of
greater and lesser version of a thing like for instance Apollo right is a sun god and he's got all
these other things but then he has Helios his his son who kind of drives the thing. You know,
right but but you don't have like equal you know D
that are the same kind of deity within a pantheon.
Right.
Right, because that's what happens when we have practical examples of assimilation,
including the assimilation of bail.
Yeah.
Which we talked about right.
Like that we talked about tonight.
So when this, when some, you know, new territory gets conquered
or a new trade deal gets made, or, you know, enters into the consciousness
of this larger unit, right, that already has this group of gods and goddesses.
Right? The attempt is made to...
folded in, right? So if there's a God in the, we'll say the major culture and the minor culture.
If there's a God in the major culture that has these attributes and these titles and these deeds,
and this new deity that's become aware of seems to have the same ones, they just get assimilated.
Yeah. Right? So, Baal becomes Zeus, Bohenair Gs. Right. Right? They say, okay, this is just the
I'm gonna hide past this.
of Zeus. Right? So we do not have any ancient evidence of that kind of assimilation with Yahweh and Bale. Right?
Because if you say that's what we're looking at with those passages that I just referenced. Okay. Oh, see, Bale has been assimilated into Yahweh.
Then I say, okay, where's the rest of the pantheon in the Israelite literature we're reading? Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, in fact, the
the only times you ever get Israel worshipping other gods, it's explicitly foreign gods and
the whole thing is condemned. Right. Right. And people like our friend Jezebel,
Israel's neighbors do not seem to recognize Yahweh as another as a hypothesis of bail. Right.
So that's going the other way. Yeah. So even the pagans aren't into it. So the pagans aren't trying
to assimilate Yahweh into their local storm.
They recognize him as different.
They recognize him as different, and there's antipathy, right?
Yeah.
Pagans are kind of famous for not really having antipathy toward each other's religions.
But they have antipathy towards Israel, and they're with it.
Right.
Yeah.
Which shows us that at the stage of these contacts, right,
which go back far before the exile, centuries before the exile, by the way,
Okay, there is seem to be something incompatible about...
at least a particular version of the worship of Yahweh,
and these other gods.
But even in a place like the Northern Kingdom of Israel,
where they're worshiping Yahweh with golden calves,
Jezebel doesn't seem to think that Bale and Yahweh
can be assimilated to each other.
Yeah, even with that common calf or bull thing going on.
So the attributes and the deeds and the titles that were
were scrubbed to Yahweh even in the northern kingdom post-gerible on the
sort of knee bat.
We're not seen by ancient people who worshiped Bale to be a version of Bale.
The guy whose name becomes emblematic, the sin of Derrabohm.
Right.
So for modern scholars to do this, they have to be really sloppy and they have to ignore
the people who actually practice these religions.
And all the evidence we have about it.
There's also no evidence of sort of disassembulation.
.
Yeah, which is that one one God splitting out into sort of multiple right.
And so we have that evidence with like we've every talked about it,
bail and Hadad, right?
We have this ball hada, right?
In the very early sources, right?
And we see that the same.
Then sort of spirit, the same sort of being is referred to as bail in one place
and had a lot in the neighboring place, right?
But we not only have evidence of that split,
but following the split.
name the Syrians and the Phoenicians don't they acknowledge yes this is the same guy
right so even though they might not know the history that at one point the two names
were directly ascribed to one being they still have the idea which again no
one in the ancient world had about Yahweh the God of Israel yeah now this is
storm god in particular but we don't have to be we can say the same thing.
The only reason treaty with Storm God is that that's the current scholarly consensus based on nothing.
Yeah. Right? And it's kind of a fun but he...
There's just as much sort of borrowed language like this about other gods in other nations, right?
So we've mentioned before on the show, every time Egypt comes up in the Old Testament,
there are all these references to the right arm.
Starting with the song of the sea, right?
after the passage through the Red Sea, but going all the way.
through into the latter prophets.
When they talk about Egypt, they talk about Yahweh
breaking the right arm of Egypt.
Because the right arm of Egypt, or the right arm of Ray,
was one of the titles given to, at different points,
the war God of Egypt and the Pharaoh.
And there's this language of Yahweh
doing mighty acts with his right arm.
Now, current scholarly consensus is that O.C.
Look, yeah.
Howe evolved from the Egyptian war, God.
Right. Right.
Because to do that, they'd have to argue the Exodus was true or something.
So they're not inclined in that way.
But that's just to show you this language, this phenomenon in the Old Testament.
Of taking the language used about the gods of the other nations and applying it to Yahweh as a way of saying that Yahweh is the truemost high God.
He's the one who brings the reins.
He's the one who controls the thunderbolt.
He's the one who gives victory in war.
etc etc etc and by the way he's the creator God
Right who created everything and caused things to be that before were not
Right that practice is all through the Old Testament and Israel's neighbors
Understood what Israel was doing when they did it. That's why there was this antipathy
Yeah, because if I was to say understood that Israel was taking shots at bail
The other stood that the Prophet Elijah was mocking bail.
They understood that Israel was saying,
your religion is bogus and ours is the truth.
Right?
They fully, their neighbors fully understood that.
Right.
And it probably pissed them off because they're like,
hello, are other neighboring religions don't do that to us.
You know, like we're fine with,
they want to worship their gods,
we worship our gods, whatever.
Yes.
You see this when Sennacherib shows up to Lacey Hitch
Jerusalem for the Assyrians.
right? And he says to him, he's like, I know, I know you've got your God who you think
is going to protect you, but lots of cities I've destroyed had gods. Right? And then, you
know, things don't go so well for Olsenacra, but, right? But like this, these were his neighbors
understood what was going on. Yeah. And, and, and then there's this constant refrain,
like it's over and over, especially in the Old Testament. But then you get echoes of it,
and repackaging of it in the New Testament.
who among the gods is like unto the outlaw Lord?
Like there's this constant rhetorical question being asked,
or occasionally the statement being made
that God is different from all the rest, all the rest.
Like none of them are like him.
You know?
Because there's no modern monotheism going on.
Right, right.
And then what you especially get,
and you get this in old Testament too,
but especially like the New Testament,
for instance, I think of St. Paul's comments on the area
you know comments on the area opogas where he's
says, you know, this is the God who made all things. Right? There's the, you know, he's the creator, which
pagan gods don't make that claim. They kind of reside within the world. I mean, they, they're sometimes
are that they were involved in creation, right? But not that there's one who made everything. You know,
he does more than that in Athens. Yeah. Yeah. Sure. Say Paul continues this thread. He quotes a
to him to Zeus and applies it to Yahweh the God of Israel.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And it says this is the one who...
actually made all men from one man and who actually in whom we live and move and have
our being. Right? Not your boy Zeus. Right? Yeah. So this is totally clear. And so what
I just did in not even that long a time, especially for this show, is layout a bunch of evidence
an argument, which the other side on this that Yahweh was a storm god.
fundamentally doesn't have. They just have, well, this is the scholarly consensus.
Yep. Yep. So, all right. Well, to wrap up this thunderous episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast,
I just wanted to, you know, make a few observations to sort of summarize. And I think the first thing
that we should point out is that, like you see this in kind of internet-religion mymology,
This idea that, you know, look at these pagan gods that have these aspects or these stories or whatever and then look at
the God of Christianity, look here, there's some similarities that
fair for must mean that the God of Christianity is derived from.
Right? As we were saying in this case, that he was a storm god.
Because look, they're the same image or the same title or the same story, right?
Often leaving aside whatever the actual discontinuities are, which as we like to point on though,
that's on this podcast are super.
important as much as the contentities, to note that things are the same or similar is
a correlation. Okay, that doesn't mean that there is a causative relationship between
those things. You know, or that they're the same thing. Just because there's a correlation
does not mean there's a causation. This is a basic logical fallacy, making them the
same thing. They're not. Correlation is not equal causation, right?
And often, as we mentioned, a lot of what's going on in the scripture and in subsequent Christian history is it's a correction of pagan stories.
It's a polemic against them.
You know, the true writer of the clouds is the son of man who is Christ.
Right. The true commander of the weather who controls the thunderbolt is God is Yahweh, not Bale, not Zeus, not Thor.
store.
Right. That's what's going on too. And then there's also, and we saw this especially with the Norse
material, but as just Father Stephen just pointed out with St Paul and Neurie Apagus,
there is an assimilation of the pagan stories as pagan stories. We'll take that and we're going to
use it to our purposes, right? So St Paul is just quoting a little verse and he's saying this actually
applies to Yahweh the God of Israel, but you get Norse Christians tell-
pulling pagan stories sometimes for the purpose of poetry, right? But I didn't see a problem
with it. I didn't see it as a simple thing to do as a Christian surrounded by Christians.
He wasn't trying to make nice with any pagans. There weren't any around. He wasn't a kind
of ecumenical gesture. They felt that these stories were helpful within their Christian
context. Right, and many of the stories are told.
sometimes as an example of what not to do. Sometimes saying, look, you can emulate and admire
this heroism, this virtue, this perseverance, whatever it is. And they were just doing, and we didn't
mention this yet in this episode, but they were just doing exactly what St. Basil and his very famous
address to young men on the right use of Greek literature by that, he means Homer and Hesiod and
and so on, that there is the right use of these things.
If there's any virtue, if there's any praise, think on these things.
And critique the things that are not virtuous and praiseworthy.
That's what's going on as well.
So Christianity has always made use of these stories.
That's how it's always been, whether it's to completely co-opt pieces of them
or to tell the story and offer commentary on it.
These are things that Christians have always done.
We do not have to be scared of that at all.
to that at all, right?
I saw someone actually commenting on this show and saying,
these guys are using pagan mythology to try to quote,
quote, reenchant the world.
And with this sort of implication of like,
they're encouraging people to become interested in paganism.
By no means.
What I encourage people to do is to become interested in stories
and to become interested in the way that Christianity
has used paganism, right?
Which always includes this polemic against the gods, right?
It's not about...
muggling anything in or making nice or any of that stuff always includes that.
Who among the gods is like unto that, Lord?
No one, no one at all, right?
So understanding all that, then we can make an application of this kind of thing ourselves
as we interpret this world and its stories and use them for preaching the gospel.
I actually mentioned a bunch of times, Marvel comics, the Marvel Cinematic Universe, especially
talk about North stuff.
And you can tell that my opinion of that is lower than the Norse pathological stories.
But I like watching those movies.
I have read those comic books and I find them useful, right?
It is a place that we can have conversations that can lead to a conversation about the
gospel or lead to discussions of virtue or whatever it might be and critique the characters
and you know say this one is good this one didn't did something
something that was not so good. Right? We can subvert even stories that may be by their
creators intended to be subversive. We can subvert the subversion because Christianity has
always done that. It's okay to continue doing it, especially because we know that we have
the great hope of the resurrection, that we know that Christ has won the victory, that
But he is the one who has defeated the serpent.
He actually did do that.
And
that his enemy, our enemy, death, its power has been broken forever.
Since we know that, then none of the rest of this has threatened us, and indeed we can
make use of it.
Because, again, that is what Christianity has always done.
Father Steven?
So yeah, they're at the end in the unprecedented fourth half.
evening show, I took some shots at scholarly consensus.
And we've talked before about how, thanks
to our 19th century German friends, pretty much all
of academic scholarship has been transformed
into sort of a vissing shaft, a scientist.
mode, a mode of aping the procedures of science. And that's had a lot of really bad results in a lot of ways
because a lot of fields have been turned into pseudoscience essentially by trying to use a methodology
that isn't really compatible with the field of inquiry.
But one positive effect that it...
it could have had, which unfortunately in a lot of cases it doesn't, would be that the
term scholarly consensus would be interpreted as a bull's eye. Something being the scholarly
consensus would make it a target. And this is true in science, right? Everybody wants to
be Einstein and come along and overturn the consensus of Newtonian physics. Right?
And you could prove that everyone wants to be that guy
because what it's Stephen Hawking do,
he started going after the consensus around Einstein
on several topics, right?
That's how it works in science.
But most of the time, when you get into any liberal arts
or quote unquote social science field,
all of a sudden, right, we de-science
and whatever the scholarly consensus is, is just true now.
It's not something we had.
It's not something we try to disassemble and take apart.
It's not now the thrust of, okay, we need to find out why we're wrong.
Maybe completely wrong.
And this boils down outside of scholarship.
What you find in a lot of academia at the graduate school level is that
that. Grad. Glory to Jesus Christ. Glory forever. You're listening to
www.EngentFaithRadio.com
In a fun way, these videos and other specially created content will be available free to children and families on the ancient priest's kids platform.
While these videos are under production, we are also raising funds to support their purchase by asking you to host a walkathon in your local parish or community.
Your walkathon can happen on any convenient date during
a month of October or the first two weeks of November. If you prefer, just let us know you're
doing it by signing up. We will provide materials for your use, including posters, organizing instructions,
and pledge sheets for participants. Learn more by emailing our development director at jmanitos
at www.entrantface.com. That's JMI.
Welcome to Tending the Garden of our Hearts.
I'm Alisa Bielotage Davis and I'm Christina Wenger.
If you've been listening to this podcast for a while, you already know that we love to
learn from the lives of the saints.
share the life.
of so many saints in previous episodes.
And we're so grateful for their example of how to follow God.
We like to study their lives and look for ways
to grow to be more like them.
We are so excited about this brand new book
that Ancient Faith has just published.
It's called 101 Orthodox Saints
and it's written by Sarah Wright and Alexandra Schmaltzbach.
And it is a beautiful, hardcover book
that tells the story of each of 101 different saints.
and every saint's page.
has fun facts and related pictures,
beautiful illustrations by Nicholas Molara.
Ancient faith has very kindly granted us permission
to share a few of the same stories with you.
And if you've been listening for the last three weeks,
we've gone through a few of them.
And this week we have our final saint, Saint Genevieve
of Paris.
So we'll be reading from the book
and then sharing some of our own insights and impressions.
And we'll ask some questions
that you can discuss with your family.
There's a part at the very beginning of the book, the introduction that has a lot of information
about saints and about why there are saints and how we treat the saints or how we ask
them to pray for us.
One of the sections that's in there is called We Are All Called To Be Saints.
It's on page 7 and...